<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doue and the serpent In which is conteined a large description of all such points and principles, as tend either to conuersation, or negotiation.</title>
            <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill), d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118774</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853981</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853981</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19386</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14084)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19386)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1040:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doue and the serpent In which is conteined a large description of all such points and principles, as tend either to conuersation, or negotiation.</title>
                  <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill), d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 92 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[reede] for Laurence L'isle, dwelling at the Tygre's head in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: D.T., i.e. Daniel Tuvill.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Another issue (STC 24394a) has cancel title page with a comma after "dove".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19386:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19386:1"/>
            <p>THE DOVE AND THE SERPENT.</p>
            <p>In which is conteined a large deſcription of all ſuch points and principles, as tend either to <hi>Conuerſation,</hi> or <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tuta velis; Tutus eris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by. <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>Laurence L'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſle,</hi> dwelling at the Tygre's head in S. Pauls Church-yard. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19386:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19386:2"/>
            <head>The ſubiect of euery ſeuerall Chapter contained in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> OF Secrecie; the meanes to attaine vnto it; the benefites it bringeth; the inconueniencies, which enſue the contrarie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Of the ſinowes of Wiſedome, wiſe diſtruſt, and ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of beleefe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Of the wiſedome of behauiour in generall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> How a man is to carrie himſelfe towards thoſe, on whom he hath dependencie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> How to conuerſe in Court, and of the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to purchaſe fauour, and ſtand ſecure from the many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which are there incident to all.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Of the manner how to conuerſe with ſtrangers in forraine regions, whereby to profit himſelfe, and benefit his Countrie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Whether a man in the performance of imployments; vpon hope of doing better, may digreſſe from the directions of him that doth imploy him: wherein the Negatiue is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> What kinde of literature and knowledge is required to the enabling of a man for the vndergoing of any buſineſſe, and the effecting of it with ſucceſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19386:3"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE.</head>
            <p>Vertue delights in thoſe alone, whoſe goodneſſe is the trueſt parallell to their greatneſſe. Her ambition hunts not after popular applauſe. <hi>Inuictam eſſe oportet manum, quae Coelum condat:</hi> The garland, which is to crowne her worth, muſt not be framed or formed by any vulgar and illiterate hands: A weaker pencill, then that of <hi>Apelles,</hi> is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to limme her Beauties forth; nor a leſſe skilfull hand then had <hi>Lyſippus,</hi> to graue in Braſſe the comelineſſe of her Proportion. Hence Sir it is, that I, her meaneſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, doe heere offer vp theſe my labours particularly to you, and indeed to none but ſuch as you:
<q>Quos manibus proprijs finxit cordata Minerua;</q> From whoſe iudicious Cenſure, whatſoeuer approbation they receiue, I ſhall account my gaine. I haue beene taught long ſince, that
<q>Principibus viris placuiſſe non vltima laus eſt;</q> And therefore with the Satyriſt,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Non ego cùm ſcribo, ſi fortè quid aptius exit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quando haec rara avis eſt, ſi quid tamen aptius exit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laudari motuam: Ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> enim mihi cornea fibra eſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Say that by chance, when I propound to write,</l>
                     <l>Some prettie thing, that's pleaſing, I endite,</l>
                     <l>Though it be rare to ſee ſuch Birds on wing;</l>
                     <l>Yet were I Author of ſome ſuch like thing,</l>
                     <l>To reape what praiſe is due I would not ſcorne:</l>
                     <l>My Boſome's made of ſofter ſtuffe then Horne.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q> 
               <hi>So without further interrupting your more ſerious imployments, I reſt, with all due reuerence,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips, D. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:19386:3"/>
            <head>Prooemium.</head>
            <p>THat vnaduiſed Rhetorician, whoſe iudgement being ſo ouerſway'd with ſelfe-conceite, as that he durſt moſt arrogantly preſume, in preſence of one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Commaunders, and beſt experienced Captaines, that thoſe times afforded, with many tedious and friuolous Diſcourſes to determine the office and dutie of a Generall, was recompenced, as he deſerued, with a diſdainefull ſmile: which being accompanied with theſe words, that <hi>had thoſe things beene handled by a Swallowe, hee would haue done the like; but if by an Eagle, haue lent them the beſt attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he could,</hi> did more manifeſtly make knowne, how much he had diſtaſted his ouerdaring weakeneſſe. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I may ſeeme at firſt in many mens iudgements wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the like cenſure and reprehenſion: but all things right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, I hope I ſhall eaſily auoyde it. For though the courſe I take ſeeme ſomewhat prepoſterous in regard of that of the ſacred <hi>Veſtalls,</hi> who firſt learned what they were to doe; ſecondly, did what they had learned; and laſt of all inſtructed others: yet is it anſwerable to that of the <hi>Pythagorians,</hi> who after three yeeres of ſilent contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, were permitted to entermeddle with publike acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to reduce their long conceiued ſpeculations, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practiſe. Now therefore with the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>— Fungar vice Cotis,<note place="margin">Horat: de arte Poët.</note> acutum</l>
                  <l>Reddere quae ferrum valet, exſors ipſa ſecandi;</l>
                  <l>Munus &amp; officium faciens nil, ipſe docebo,</l>
                  <l>Quid deceat, quid non; quò virtus, quò ferat error:</l>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
         <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19386:4"/>
            <p>for whoſe ſafer Conuoy, hee hath engaged his fidelity. Hee ſhall meete with many Pyrats, that will ſtriue to boord him, not ſo much for the Veſſell, as the burden; and this they will be maiſters of, or their liues ſhall pay the forfeiture of their miſcarrying: But the Tongue is the Sterne of this great Caracke, which whoſoeuer hath the skill to guide, may eaſily diſappoint them in their aymes.</p>
            <p>It was the manner of thoſe ancient Champions, which by the Greekes were called <hi>Pancratiastae,</hi> to ſtand, being ſummoned to fight, with their armes lift vp on high, fortifying as with a Trench, their head and mouth, with their oppoſed hands; and ſetling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in a readynes, before the beginning of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, either to put by the blowes of their <hi>Antagon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſts,</hi> or make them feele the heauy waight of theirs. In the like poſture ſhould the minde of a wiſe man be, againſt the ryotous and wanton violence of iniurious perſons; <hi>Erecta eſſe debet, ardua, ſepta, ſolida, expedita, nunquàm connivens, nuſquàm aciem ſuam flecters;</hi> but continually producing Counſailes and aduiſe, againſt the Batteries and Aſſaults of the deceitfull, againſt the ſnares and treacheries of the vniuſt, as the onely armes and hands, whereby to repell their force, and ſecure himſelfe from being ſuddenly ſurprized. He muſt be like thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall creatures in <hi>Ezechiell,</hi> full of Eyes, (that is) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding vigilant, and circumſpect in his proceedings: But aboue all, hee muſt put a bridle in his mouth, and curbe his tongue, from being too extrauagant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ech</hi> is the onely Character, by which a man expreſſeth himſelfe vnto the life; A Picture ſheweth vs but his outward lineaments, but in this, the nature and qualitie of his minde is oftentimes decyphered to the full.</p>
            <q>Laudibus arguitur vini vinoſus Homerus.</q>
            <p>And hence no doubt, came that of <hi>Socrates. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19386:4"/> vt te vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eam.</hi> That Noble man, which came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Painters ſhoppe, drew by his outward preſence all due obſeruance, &amp; reſpect, euen from the Maiſter; but when he began to ſpeake, the boyes brake forth in laughter at his weakeneſſe; And indeed, by nothing better then her note, can we diſtinguiſh the Bird.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of Geeſe, that, when at the change of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they paſſe from <hi>Cilicia,</hi> ouer the mountaine <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> which abounds with Eagles: they carry ſtones in their bills, for feare their crie ſhould diſcouer them to their enemies. Reaſon ſhould teach vs that, which Nature hath inſtructed them; but alas, it is a thing of greater difficultie then ſo. For it is not poſſible that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſhould moderate his tongue, who hath not firſt of all tamed his affections.</p>
            <p>The ſonne of <hi>Croeſus</hi> was dumbe euen from his birth, yet when the Souldier had aduanced his ſword to cut the threed of his fathers life, the violence of his paſſion remoou'd the impediment of his ſpeech, and he cried out, <hi>O ſtay thy hand, It is the King thou haſt at that aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage;</hi> This which through naturall loue was cauſed in him, hath very ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the diſordered &amp; irregular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Minde,</hi> bin wrought in others. <hi>Philotas</hi> by his ambitious vaunts, and windie oſtentations, made a broade paſſage to his own confuſion. <hi>Sampſon,</hi> by dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying too much with his <hi>Dalilah,</hi> betrayde his life and ſafety to the <hi>Philiſtims:</hi> And <hi>Claudius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tac: Annal: Lib: <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> by ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting forth a word in his diſtemperature, gaue <hi>Agrippina</hi> warning to haſten his deſtruction. I will not ſtand to amplifie this point with any more particulars, but (in a word) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe thee, whoſoeuer thou art, that ſhalt thruſt thy ſelfe abroad into the day, ſo to compoſe thy inward minde, that thy outward carriage may continually be calme and quiet. For thence it is, that all the parts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our bodie haue their ſtormie motions;
<q>Hunc igitur fraenis, hunc tu compeſce Catena:</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19386:5"/>
            <p>If this be ſetled once, the Tongue cannot miſcarrie. We may obſerue in <hi>Homer,</hi> that ſuch as are commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him for their wiſedome, are likewiſe ſaide to bee moſt ſparing of their ſpeech: Hee makes <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> after his returne, to giue his ſonne this charge;
<q>
                  <l>If thou be mine, &amp; from my bloud deriu'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Odyſſ</note>Let none perceiue <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> is arriu'd:</l>
                  <l>Let not <hi>Laertes,</hi> nor <hi>Eumaeus</hi> knowe it,</l>
                  <l>Nor vnto any of my Seruants ſhowe it, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſpeake truth, it is impoſſible, according to that ſaying of <hi>Demaratus.</hi> A foole ſhould hold his peace.<note place="margin">Plutar. de Audit.</note> So that <hi>Spintharus</hi> did not meanely commend <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> when he ſaid, He nere had entercourſe with any in all his life, that knew ſo much, and ſpake ſo little as he did. It is requiſite therefore that they, which take vpon them the performance of any publike office, ſhould firſt bend their endeuours to the attayning of Concealement; For without this,
<q>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tora bobus arant, &amp; arenis pemina mandant;</q> They can neither be profitable to themſelues, nor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable to others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>An open mouth, ſayeth</hi> Plutarke) <hi>ſerues the Maiſter to no other vſe, then doth a houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a doore, or a purſe without a ſtring.</hi> Hee muſt not in any wiſe be like that place in the City of <hi>Olympias,</hi> which for the often reſounding of one and the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame voyce, by reaſon of diuers and ſundry refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in it, was not without iuſt, and due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſurnamed <hi>Heptaphonos.</hi> For howſoeuer it be a very difficult thing to reſtrain the tongue from intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancie in this kinde, and that many men are of ſuch a temper, that they could with greater patience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to carry burning coales in their breſts, then <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets;</hi> Whereupon it often-times falls out, that thoſe things which are whiſpered in the eare, are preſently after publiſhed in the market; yet is there no excuſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19386:5"/> wherewith to colour ſuch a defect in one of publike place. For beſides an imputation of weakeneſſe which he brings thereby vpon himſelfe, he doth firſt of all controll the very purpoſe and intent of Nature, who to ſhew vs the vnrulineſſe of the tongue, and with what ſtrictneſſe it is to be obſerued, hath as it were impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it in the mouth; chain'd it with ſinowes to the throate; wall'd it about with gummes; hedg'd it in on euery ſide with teeth; and for feare it might any way breake forth, ſhut it vp cloſely with the lips, as with a two-leau'd gate, ſo that his iudgement, and diſcretion, which haue the charge and cuſtodie thereof, cannot but be liable to Cenſure, if it make eſcape.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he doth digreſſe from Reaſon, which confirmes vnto vs euery moment by infinite examples, That the ſafetie of the tongue is the tree of life; and hee which preſerueth it, according to that of the wiſe man, <hi>Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>opir quabit Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Hor. Carm. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Od. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> he maketh himſelfe thereby an enemy to all Societie;
<q>
                  <l>— vetabo qui C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reris ſacrum</l>
                  <l>Vulgarit arcanae, ſub ijſdem</l>
                  <l>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> trabibus; fragil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mecum</l>
                  <l>Soluat f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>elum —</l>
               </q> ſayth the Poet; And in an other place he giueth euery one this caution:
<q>Percun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ator<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m fugito; nam garruius idem eſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, he doth breake and violate the lawes of Nations. Amongſt the Perſians, <hi>Lingua magis castiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur,</hi> ſayth <hi>Q. Curtius, quàm vli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m probrum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Q. Curt. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> the tongue was more ſeuerely puniſhed then any crime: <hi>nec mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam rem magis ſuſtine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i potuiſſe crediderunt ab eo cuitacere graue eſſet, quod facil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it eſſe Natura;</hi> yea, they diſabled him, from euer hauing the managing of any waightie charge, that had not in him the power of Concealement: and by this diſcipline they preuailed ſo farre, that neither feare nor hope, could euer drawe from them the leaſt knowledge of that, which was not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19386:6"/> to be knowne: witneſſe <hi>Alexander,</hi> who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ligent enquities, and induſtrious ſearches which he made after the plots and proiects of <hi>Darius,</hi> could neuer learne the courſe of his proceedings. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Egyptians</hi> likewiſe, it was a capitall offence. A Virgin in the Temple of <hi>Iſis,</hi> was defloured by a Prieſt,<note place="margin">Diodor. Sic.</note> who hauing for the better compaſſing of his luſtfull deſires, relyed vpon the ſecrecie of a third, was by him betrayed vnto the Magiſtrate, who pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ſentence of death againſt the malefactors, and branded him, for the hyre of his falſehood, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and ſhamefull baniſhment. And in other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes where this was neuer puniſht as a fault, the contrary hath ſtill beene honoured and rewarded as a Vertue. <hi>Eſt &amp; fideli tuta ſilentio Merces.</hi> —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dionyſius</hi> gaue ſtraight commaundement, the head of <hi>Brias,</hi> one of the Gentlemen of his Chamber, ſhould be cut off, for telling <hi>Plato,</hi> who had demaunded of him what the Tyrant did, That he had ſtripped himſelf by reaſon of the heate, and was painting in a Table. So that laſt of all, he makes a blot of his owne Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and hazards vpon the vncertaine chances of the Dice, his deareſt ſafetie.</p>
            <p>Vipers are torne in ſunder with the bringing forth of their young; and ſecret words iſſuing out of the mouth, bring with them the vtter ruine and ſubuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that reuealed them: It is an oracle vttered vnto vs by the mouth of Wiſedome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 13 <hi>verſe</hi> 3.</note> That he which keepeth his mouth, keepeth his life: And indeede it is as true as tride — <hi>Non tacuiſſe nocet, nocet eſſe locutum;</hi> according to the ſaying of that good <hi>Simonides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt other Hieroglyphikes, by which the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians did ſhadow Silence forth, they made the Quince-tree one, whoſe fruite hath the proportion of the heart, and whoſe leafe is faſhioned like the tongue of man: to ſignifie thereby vnto vs, that Speech which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19386:6"/> is the fruite as it were of the Vnderſtanding, ſhould be perpetually faſtened vnto that, and not to this. Yea, the ſpirit of Truth enformeth vs, that he which hath knowledge, ſpareth his words; but the mouth of a foole is his owne deſtruction, and his lips are a ſnare for his ſoule. Wherefore he that is familiarly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his owne infirmities, and findeth in himſelfe this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this talkatiue intemperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, let him ſtand aloofe, and not raſhly vndertake any waightie, or important charge; but ſalute it at a ſafe and fearleſſe diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as young <hi>Hyppolitus</hi> did the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <hi>Venus,</hi> or his preſumptuous ouer-weening, will haue a tragicall <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The times are dangerous and deceitfull in which we liue. The World affoords vs almoſt nothing now, which is not perſonated and diſguiſed. Amongſt men there are many, — <hi>Qui fronte politi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perſ: Sat: <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>Aſtutam vapido ſeruant ſub pectore Vuloem.</q>
            </p>
            <p>They haue honie in their mouthes, but a Razour at their girdles; and as the <hi>Comike</hi> ſaith,
<q>
                  <l>Compoſita dicta pectore euolvunt ſuo,</l>
                  <l>Quae cum comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nas dicta factis diſcrepant.<note place="margin">Plaut.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, the <hi>Owle</hi> hath learnd to counterfaite the <hi>Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale:</hi> and <hi>Sathan</hi> that hee may the better worke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a weake beliefe, hath faſhioned his Tongue to the Dialect of Angels. <hi>Simolicitie</hi> lyeth ſpeechleſſe, and <hi>Vpright-dealing</hi> is ready to giue vp the Ghoſt; the Bell hath oftentimes rung out for them; by reaſon wherof, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſimulation</hi> hath long ſince entered vpon their Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; and like a cunning Vſurper, enthron'd her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe within the hearts and mindes of fraile <hi>Mortalitie;</hi> So that fewe are left, and thoſe not eaſily to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, which are not as the Poet ſaith,
<q>Introrſum turpes, ſpecioſi pell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> decora.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Euery man is now become a <hi>Sydonian,</hi> and hath his <hi>Baal</hi> to himſelfe: whilſt he that is the GOD of Gods,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19386:7"/> of power and Maieſtie ſo infinite, that (as th' <hi>Aegyptians</hi> cauſed to bee written on their Temple Gates) hee is,<note place="margin">Hermes. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m: <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Whatſoeuer hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beene, is or ſhall bee,</hi> is made the ſubiect of his Helliſh laughter. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> and <hi>Gaine,</hi> are almoſt in as great eſteeme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, as <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> were amongſt the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omanes,</hi> their Temples are alike contriu'd; It is impoſſible to come vnto the laſt, but by the former: And hence proceedeth that of the <hi>Satyriſt:</hi>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Iuuenal. Sat. <hi>13.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>Quae tam feſta dies, vt ceſſet prodere furem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Perfidiam, fraudes, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> omni ex crimine lucrum</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quaeſitum, &amp; partos gladio, vel pixide nummos.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No day ſo holie, but it ſtill bewrayes</l>
                     <l>Thefts, guiles, deceits, and treacherous aſſayes:</l>
                     <l>Goods lewdly got, by Crimes, and vile offences,</l>
                     <l>By murthers, poyſonings, and vnchaſt pretences.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true, that in a mans owne priuate buſineſſes, hee may aſſume what libertie he pleaſe; but in thoſe things which concerne a third, he muſt be very wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie how hee doth proceede. <hi>Icaru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to ſatisfie his daring minde, may freely (peraduenture) &amp; without controul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſoare aboue the ſtrength of his waxen wings, as long as the diſaſtrous euent of his preſumption, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it ſelfe no farther, then the compaſſe of his owne graue: But <hi>Phaeton,</hi> muſt of neceſſitie bee blamed, if wilfully and vnaduiſedly, hee vndergoe a taske, the weake performance whereof, brings nothing but confuſion to himſelfe, and others. And this is that our SAVIOVR CHRIST ſo ofte inculcated to his Diſciples, when bidding them <hi>beware of men,</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto them the <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edome of the Serpent,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his Church; but the <hi>Innoce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Sim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ie</hi> of <hi>Doues,</hi> in regard of themſelues. It behooueth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19386:7"/> one therefore to take heede, how, and to whom he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen himſelf at any time, for feare he falſifie the truſt which is repoſed in him, and by ſo doing endanger all.</p>
            <p>Let him imitate that <hi>Graecian</hi> of former times, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told that his breath did ſmell, Anſwered, It was by reaſon of the many <hi>Secrets,</hi> which had a long while laine rotting, and putrifying within him.</p>
            <p>Let his <hi>Boſome</hi> be like the <hi>Lyons denne</hi> in the Apologue; towards the mouth whereof, the Prints and prickings of ſundrie ſorts of Beaſts might eaſily be diſcerned, <hi>Sed nulla retrorſum,</hi> but from thence none at all.</p>
            <p>Let him alwayes talke with <hi>Harpocrates,</hi> at the ſigne of the Finger on the Mouth; and learne of <hi>Anacharſis,</hi> that the <hi>Tongue</hi> hath neede of a more ſtrong reſtraint then <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let him not be too curious with them of <hi>Bethſhemeſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. 2. <hi>King:</hi> 20. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</note> in the ſearch of other mens <hi>Secrets,</hi> nor yet too careles with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> in the diſcouery of his owne. <hi>Moralitie</hi> giueth him a prohibition for the one, and a precept for the other.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Arcanum ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tu ſcrutaberis vllius vnquàm;</l>
               <l>Commiſſum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> teges, &amp; vino tortus, &amp; irâ.<note place="margin">Hor: Epiſt. <hi>18.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And indeed it is a profanation of dutie, to publiſh any thing we ſhould not. Thoſe things therefore which are to be concealed, let him conceale them, — <hi>vt Curia Martis Athenis;</hi> as cloſe as either Silence or Darknes will affoord him meanes to keepe them both from Eye and Eare: for the better effecting whereof, there is neceſſarily required in him a <hi>Wiſe diſtruſt,</hi> and <hi>flowneſſe of Beliefe,</hi> wherewith his breſt muſt ſo equally be ballanced, that he may ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily run on, without ſuffering ſhipwracke in ſuch a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and dangerous Courſe.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19386:8"/>
            <p>vnto our Sauiour Chriſt with a deceitfull and captious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatorie,<note place="margin">
                  <p>prayſes of whoſe mouths are witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts: of thoſe are theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Poet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Si vltra pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum laudâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, baccare frontem cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gite ne v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti noceat ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la lingua fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo. Virg. Ecl.</hi> 7. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 26.</p>
               </note> and ſayd vnto him, Maiſter, Maiſter, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that he perceiuing himſelfe ſo honoured and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by them, might ſimply peradventure, and without miſtruſt, diſcouer and reueale vnto them the ſecrets of his heart: but alas! they miſtooke their aime, they miſſed their marke. He that intuitiuely knew all things, did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe know their ſalutation to be nothing elſe, but a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous and treacherous inſinuation; and therfore how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he accepted of the like titles from the mouth of his Diſciples; yet heere the text ſayth of him, That he ſtouped downe, and with his finger wrote vpon the ground; to ſhew, that he was not delighted with their vanitie, and that he knew the ſcope and drift of their intent. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer there are many ſo weake of vnderſtanding, that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring others by their owne ſimplicitie, they ſuffer both Diſcourſe and Iudgement to be ſubdued by outward cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, and led in triumph by the formall apparance of deluding Sycophants. Yea the wiſeſt, if neuer ſo little Iouially diſpoſed, can hardly keepe themſelues from nib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at this bait. Men for the moſt part are like the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke, of which the Poet writes;
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laudatas oſtendit avis Iunonia pennas;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si tacitus ſpectes illa recondit opes;</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Her prayſed plumes great Iunôs bird ſpreads forth,</l>
                     <l>But view'd with ſilence, ſhe conceales her worth:</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Such as haue any ſenſe at all, are ſenſible in this; there is no Stoike but deſireth it, no Cynike but delighteth in it. But they that ſhall conſider with themſelues, that <hi>Eſops</hi> Fox did not praiſe the Crow, but to beguile him of his preye, will peraduenture be warie, how they be tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and led away with ſuch vaine perſwaſions. There is in ſpeeches of this nature a certaine ſweetneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 18. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 106.</note> 
               <hi>quae irrepit &amp; blanditur, &amp; non aliter, quàm ebrietas, aut amor ſecreta prodit,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19386:8"/> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> which hauing ſtolne into the heart, doth with a tickling kind of motion ſo pleaſe and ſooth it, that no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then Loue or Wine, it cauſeth it to vent the moſt retired Secrets: but Wiſedome preſcribeth vs an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote, and biddeth vs ſtop our Eares againſt the Charmes and incantations of ſuch Sirens, and not ſuffer our ſelues to be like Pitchers, led vp and downe by the ſiniſter adu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of ſuch double and clouen-hearted Paraſites, that like cunning Anglers doe draw vs on to ſwallow downe the bait, that in the end they may hang vs on the hooke.</p>
            <p>There are others, that by enforcing an imaginarie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, endeuour to extort a truth; and this as it is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually practiſed, ſo is it ſeldome vneffected: prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the thing obiected be a matter of more conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and ſuch as would redound, if iuſtified, with ſcandall to the partie that ſhould reporte it. For feeling himſelfe ſo vrged, hee will inſtantly, to cleare himſelfe of the greater imputation, not ſtick peraduenture to confeſſe the leſſer. But theſe may eaſily be preuented, if wee can keepe our ſelues from falling into paſſion, and ſeeme but lightly touched with their obiections.</p>
            <p>There are ſome againe,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that on the ſuddaine and vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, doe ſet vpon a man, and with ſome ſhorte, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected queſtion labour to ſurprize him: Theſe, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they ſeeldome make a full and perfect diſcouery of what they looke for, yet hauing driuen him as it were, by this meanes to a ſtand,<note place="margin">Ita intimos mentis affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus proditor vultus enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat, vt in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um imago extat animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Plin. Sec.</note> they thinke they may eaſily (as by obſeruing the manner of his reply, by noting the priuate and ſubtile motions of his countenance, and the faſhions of his behauiour) collect ſome probability of their ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; which done, they bend all their practiſe to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forme, and ceaſe not their purſuite, till they be mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the game: But the onely meanes to delude their expectation, is eyther to ſlight their queſtion; to expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate their opinion; to anſwere little, &amp; what they leaſt looke for; or in ſome caſes not to anſwere at all; but by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19386:9"/> way of oppoſition, and compenſation to confront their interrogatories and demands, with others of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: As our Sauiour CHRIST did in the Goſpell, when the high Prieſts and Elders of the people came vnto him, and asked him by what authoritie he did thoſe things, and from whence hee had the power to doe them; <hi>Tell mee,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Baptiſme of</hi> Iohn,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 21. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24:</note> 
               <hi>Is it of heauen, or of men?</hi> and with this <hi>Dilemma,</hi> this two-edged argument, hee cut the throate of their inquiſitiueneſſe. There is another exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the like nature, expreſſed by the Poet in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene <hi>Damoetas</hi> and <hi>Menalcas:</hi> the one ſaith,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Virgil. Eclog. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note>Dic quibus in terris, &amp; eris mihi magnus <hi>Apollo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tres pateat Coeli ſpatium non amplius vlnas.</l>
               </q> And the other, not able (it may be) to expound his riddle, or at leaſt not willing, requiteth him with the like:
<q>
                  <l>Dic quibus in terris inſcripti nomina Regum</l>
                  <l>Naſcantur flores, &amp; <hi>Phyllida</hi> ſolus habeto.</l>
               </q> And this is a iuſt and lawfull retribution, and nothing elſe then to giue our aduerſarie the foyle at his owne weapon.</p>
            <p>To be briefe, there are ſome that will not let to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance many feined matters on themſelues, by way of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation, or vpon others by way of approbation, that they may drawe from their auditorie a true confeſſion of the like. Of theſe we muſt take heede, and withall, be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently carefull, that they worke not vpon our weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and diſaduantages; or make vs the ſubiect of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments. And that we may the better ſecure our ſelues from them, we muſt know it is their vſuall practiſe, when they meete with any ſo firmely ſetled in their diſpoſition that they cannot leade them; ſo cloſe and priuate in their deſires, that they cannot winne them; ſo furniſhed with rules and principles of wiſe preuention, that they cannot
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19386:9"/> awe them; to faſten vpon their friends, factions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendences, or others that are intereſted in them, and ſo gouerne them; And hence proceeded that of <hi>Sampſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Had ye not ploughed with my heifer, yee had not found out my riddle.</hi> Wherefore it is good, neuer to impart our mindes, but where it much importeth; and in matters of any moment to be alwayes doubtfull of the worſt.<note place="margin">Euripides.</note> For as the Poet ſayth,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>:<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Epichar.</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then wiſe diſtruſt there is not any thing,</l>
                     <l>To mortall men that can more profit bring.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But if it be grounded vpon vaine imaginations and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, it is either an argument of weakeneſſe, or of baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and who ſo vſeth it, muſt of neceſſitie be thought a traitour to humane Societie. For as to beleeue all things is childiſh, ſo to beleeue nothing is meerely brutiſh. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <hi>Multi fallere docuerunt, dum timent falli;</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca.</hi> It is therefore requiſite in Ciuill policie, and no way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating, as I take it, from the rules and precepts of Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, euen in matters where there is greateſt cauſe of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, eſpecially if the parties be ſuch as otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue reſpect, ſo to diſguiſe his feares and iealouſies,<note place="margin">Frontem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periat, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tegat. Cic. pro Cn. Plan.</note> that the diſcouerie may neither proue offenſiue vnto them, nor hurtfull to himſelfe. There is no <hi>Argus,</hi> but, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his wakefull obſeruation, ſhall finde a <hi>Mercurie</hi> to delude him. They that are free and liberall of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, are often-times the moſt ſecure from danger, if they erre not in the choyce of their ſubiect; whereas theſe <hi>Saturnines</hi> that ſtand continually vpon their watch and ward, and ſpeake not but with <hi>Pythagoricall</hi> ſuſpenſion, giue publike notice to the world, that there is ſome-what in their keeping, which they would not willingly loſe; and by this meanes whet and ſharpen the wits of the more curious ſort againſt themſelues, that in the end they cannot but be made the ſpoyle and prey of their Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19386:10"/> And with this agreeth that worthy ſpeech of the Philoſophers,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. <hi>lib.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Multi aperta tranſeunt, condita &amp; obstruſa ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>r: f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m ſignata ſollicitant; vile videtur quicquid patet; aperta effractarius praeteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: hos mores habet populus, hos imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſmu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quiſque, in ſecreta irrumpere cupit.</hi> But I will ſlide from hence to that which doth remaine, as loth to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Reader with prolixitie, or giue him occaſion to diſtaſte the reſt through loathed ſatietie.</p>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the wiſedome of Behauiour in generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wiſedome which is required in one of publike imployment, is either wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>behauiour,</hi> or wiſedome of <hi>negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</hi> which in a word is nothing but the <hi>Doue,</hi> and the <hi>Serpent.</hi> For as concerning the firſt; he muſt be kinde and courteous towards all men; full of mildneſſe and affabilitie in his diſcourſe; full of ſobrietie, and appliable demeanour in his conuerſation. The minde of a wiſe man is by the mouth of <hi>Salomon</hi> compared to a glaſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 27. <hi>verſe</hi> 19.</note> in which the formes and Characters of all diuerſitie of Natures, and of all varietie of Cuſtomes are repreſented: ſo that hence I conclude with the Poet, that, <hi>Qui ſapit innumer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moribus aptus erit.</hi> He will not like a <hi>Cato</hi> faſhion himſelfe to none; nor like a <hi>Catiline</hi> conforme himſelfe to all: the one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth exceedingly of wickedneſſe, the other ſomewhat too much of wilfulneſſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Eſt modus in rebus, ſunt certi denique fines,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Horat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Sat. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>Quos vltrà citràque neo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it conſiſtere rectum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>He will therefore out of his owne diſcretion ſo leuell forth his carriage, that it may hold a certaine ſpecious
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19386:10"/> kinde of correſpondencie with moſt, and not giue by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of diſtance, or diſproportion, occaſion of offence to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: with ſome actually &amp; indeede; with otherſome appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, &amp; with relation onely to <hi>Societie.</hi> For this, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we diſlike the vneuenneſſe of mens proceedings, muſt alwayes be preſerued and kept vnviolated.</p>
               <p>He muſt not diſapproue of whatſoeuer is not bounded with the circumference of his owne opinion, or tendeth not to the ſame Center: nor giue his iudgement vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, though he be neuer ſo well able to decide it, but with Apologies, and Cautions; to the intent that ſuch as are in conference with him may haue no cauſe, either to enuy his knowledge, or bluſh at their owne ignorance.</p>
               <p>He muſt not like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Aſſe grow proud and inſolent of his employments, nor thinke the better of himſelfe becauſe of his burthen: but entertaine ſuch priuate gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and fauors as are ſhowne him, with a ſetled modeſtie: &amp; neuer publiſh them, but with an abaſement of his owne merit, aſcribing all ſuch accidents, more to the authors fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie, or his owne externall felicitie, then to any skill or vertue that is inherent.</p>
               <p>He muſt auoyde all windie oſtentation, which by the force of <hi>Selfe-Conceite,</hi> may be drawne from any ſuruey he hath taken of his owne worthineſſe. It is an vnſeemely thing for any man to be the trumpet of his owne ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: and whoſoeuer it is that ſtriues to bee both <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Achilles; Virgil</hi> and <hi>Aeneas;</hi> he doth but manifeſt his owne weakneſſe, and want of wit. For his actions (if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing be in him) will in time proue ſufficient blazoners of his worth. Let vs but rightly caſt vp our accounts, &amp; we ſhall ſtreightway finde, that wee can neuer ſpeake of our ſelues but with ſome preiudice: Our proper taxations are receiued ſtill as ſetled truthes: but the commendations which wee giue our owne deſeruings, cannot eſcape the cenſure of Misbeliefe.<note place="margin">Plin: Epiſt: <hi>8.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Beſides, <hi>quod magnificum referente alio fuiſſet, ipſo qui geſſerat,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plinie) recenſente vaneſcit:</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19386:11"/> little Oare, we ſtill dig further on in hope of more, flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our expectation with this conceit, that ſurely ſo ſmall a quantitie was not alone, and impute the not attaining it, to nothing elſe but our owne vnhappineſſe. It will not therefore, I take it, be much amiſſe for any one to aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage himſelfe, ſo often as he ſeeth occaſion, by the vſe and practiſe of this principle.</p>
               <p>In contracts of loue and amitie, I could aduiſe euery man to be alwayes mindfull of that of <hi>Martial,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Lib.</hi> 12. <hi>Epigr.</hi> 34.</note>
                           <hi>Si vitare velis acerbu quaedam,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Et triſtes animi cauere morſus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nulli te facias nimis ſodalem;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Gaudebis minus &amp; minus dolebis.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Who liſt not taſte of bitter diſcontent,</l>
                        <l>But the ſad bitings of the minde preuent,</l>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Caeſar, è duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conſula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus comperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceium ſibi adiunxit, pactus vt is, quoniam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior gratia eſſet, pecunia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que polleret, nummos de ſuo communi nomine per centurias pronuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Sueton. Iul. diſtinct. <hi>19.</hi>
                           </note>Muſt make himſelfe too fellow-like with none;</l>
                        <l>Leſſe cauſe hee'l haue to grieue, leſſe cauſe to mone.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> Or at leaſt that he make choyce of none to be familiarly acquainted with him, but ſuch as are honeſt and vertuous; of ſuch as may delight him in their conuerſation, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a neereneſſe in manners, and a likeneſſe in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or laſt of all, of ſuch as are able to help him in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of his affaires, by their diſcreet and prouident di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, or furniſh him if neede require, with ſupplyes of an other nature, for the better furtherance of his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. For this indeede is that ſame three-fold baſe, on which, as <hi>Plutarke</hi> ſayth, all friendſhip muſt be rays'd, or it will quickly faile.</p>
               <p>There are ſome, that in the ſunny vp-ſpring of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are with the Swallow ſtill at hand, and ready as it were to doe vs all the ſeruiceable offices they can: but when the winter of our happineſſe doth once approach, behold, they ſuddainly vaniſh, and grow ſtrangers to vs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19386:11"/> in our greateſt neede. Some againe, as indeed,
<q>Tuta, frequenſque via eſt, per amicifallere nomen,</q> that will not ſtick to proteſt their pure and ſingular affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards vs, when the ſcope of all their aimes is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deceiue vs. The <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in their <hi>hieroglyphikes</hi> were wont to ſhadow theſe forth by the Pye, which is white before, but black behinde. And in truth, as <hi>Triphon</hi> the Grammarian ſayd, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Mendacium in extrema parte nigreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</note> Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is counterfait, and adulterate, though it eye vs with neuer ſo faire a face, if we marke it well, we ſhall finde it black alwayes towards the tayle. That precept therefore of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> deſerues our approbation, by which he war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not to admit a black-tayld hypocrite into our friendſhip. Laſtly, there are others ſo voyd of all ciuilitie, ſo deſtitute of all humanitie, that out of a vile and ſlauiſh diſpoſition, the better to preuent their aſſociates, neighbours, and allyes, from preſuming any thing vpon their kindneſſe, are not aſhamed to giue out, That the onely way to haue a friend, is to make no vſe of him; intending it ſhould ſeeme, like churliſh <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals,</hi> to taſte of no mans cup themſelues, becauſe they would haue no man to taſte of theirs: but theſe are vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be contemned and deſpiſed, as the deteſted out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts of Societie. For as the Poet ſayth of riches,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Quò mihi diuitiae, ſi non conceditur vti?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With wealthie ſummes of gold what ſhould I doo,</l>
                        <l>Vnleſſe I might both haue, and vſe them too?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> I likewiſe ſay of this.</p>
               <p>To conclude, he muſt be carefull, that as his ſpeech is eloquent, his vtterance be likewiſe pleaſing and amiable. <hi>Mercurie</hi> cannot well be ſeparated from the Graces, nor they from him, but the muſicall conſent of ciuill Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation will fall out to be very harſh and diſcordant. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, he muſt indeauour that his words and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance may ſeeme like parallell lines deriued equally from one Center, that the reſeruedneſſe of the laſt may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19386:12"/> the credit of the former, and make good meaning liable to miſconſtruction. In a word, he muſt in all things be free from affectation. There is nothing more vndecent in a man, then an ouercurious obſeruance of decencie. To intend the faſhioning of an externall carriage &amp; beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſo much, as to let it paſſe into affectation, is euen by the ſhalloweſt vnderſtandings condemned as ridiculous, and accepted of all men (to the great diſabling of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie that vſeth it) as a moſt euident argument and proofe of weakeneſſe and indiſcretion. Wherefore let him auoide all ſingularitie, both in action, geſture, and diſcourſe, and ſo compoſe and gouerne himſelfe in all ſuch points as appertaine to conuerſation; that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his care and circumſpection in declining from what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is incongruous and abſurd, that which that <hi>Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> ſayd of <hi>Ianus,</hi> may deſeruedly be pronounced of him.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Perſ. Satyr. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>O Iane, à tergo, quem nulla Ciconia pinſit,</l>
                  <l>Nec manus auriculas imitata eſt mobilis albas,</l>
                  <l>Nec linguae, quantum ſitiat Canis Apula, tantum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>All ſuch occaſions being farre remooued, as might any way betray his credit, to the traducements of a vulgar and illiterate laughter. Laſtly,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Hor. Epiſt. <hi>18.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                           </note>
                           <hi>Non ſua laudabit ſtudia, aut aliena reprendet:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nec cum venari volet ille, poëmata panget.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>His proper courſes he ſhall ne're commend,</l>
                        <l>Nor by reproouing other mens offend:</l>
                        <l>Ne when his friend by hunting ſport would finde,</l>
                        <l>Shall he incline to Poëtrie his minde.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vespaſian</hi> got the ill will of <hi>Nero</hi> by ſleeping at his mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall recreations; whereas <hi>Pamphilus</hi> had the loue of all by obſeruing the former.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Terent. in Andr.</note>Sic vita erat, <hi>ſaith his father,</hi> ſacilè omnes perferre ac pati</l>
                  <l>Cum quibuſcunque erat vnà, ijs ſeſe dedere,</l>
                  <l>Eorum obſequi ſtudijs, advorſus nemini</l>
                  <l>Nunquam praeponens ſe alijs —:</l>
               </q>
               <p>and hence he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19386:12"/> that whoſoeuer ſhal carry himſelf in the like kind, <hi>facillimè</hi>
                  <q>Sine invidia inveniat laudem, &amp; amicos paret.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. How a man is to carrie himſelfe towards thoſe, on whom he hath <hi>any dependencie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer hee be that dependeth not entirely vpon himſelfe, but hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in his fortunes to ſome of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler ranke, from whom hee hopes, by doing him all the offices of a dutifull and faithfull ſeruant, to drawe ſome meanes where-with to raiſe the low-built roofe of his eſtate; let him firſt of all, that he may the better inſtate himſelfe within his grace and fauour, to whom he ſtandeth ſo deuoted, and as I may ſay, get ground of his affections, obſerue his nature and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and when he hath diſcouered and found out his humours and his inclinations, endeuour, ſo they be not vitious and diſhoneſt (for I would not that he ſhould like <hi>Tigellinus,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reporteth,<note place="margin">Tacit. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>principem ſocietate ſcelerum obſtringere,</hi> ſeeke to endeare his Maiſter to himſelfe by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king part in his vnbounded diſſolutions) by fulfilling them, to giue him the beſt contentment and ſatisfaction that poſſibly he may.</p>
               <p>Let him neuer abſent himſelfe long from about his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but continually be at hand, and in fight; yea, let him feigne occaſions of acceſſe, rather then want them, that ſo by entertaining a familiar kinde of priuacie with him, hee may (by little and little) winde, and as it were ſerue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe through his externall ſhew of diligence into his beſt affections. Further, let him be very carefull neuer to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19386:13"/> his preſence,<note place="margin">Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſit, nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium aliquod celeriter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere, oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit nobis trium verboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ille titulus, quem Pontico tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpho Caeſar praetulit. <hi>VENI. VIDI. VICI.</hi> Suet. Iul. <hi>37</hi>
                  </note> but with a plauſible and cheerefull countenance; and at all times ſhew a ſpeciall alacritie in the ready embracing of his will and commaundements. Let him as the childe of <hi>Obedience,</hi> and the friend of <hi>Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> be continually ready to vndergoe vpon the leaſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, what charge ſoeuer ſhalbe impoſed vpon him, and afterwards effect it, with ſuch quicknes and celeritie, that if in the managing thereof, his cunning and ſufficiencie be neuer noted, his expedition may.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Plaut. in Aulular.</note>Herile imperium ediſcat, vt quod frons velit oculi ſciant;</l>
                  <l>Quod iubeat, citis quadrigis citius properet exequi.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Let him not bee like <hi>Phoebus</hi> his Crowe, which hauing bin ſent by him in haſte for water to the running ſprings, lighted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a tree which was full of figges, but ſo greene, they could not well be gathered, and therfore as the Poet relateth it,
<q>
                     <l>Immemor Imperij ſediſſe ſub arbore fertur,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Ouid. Faſt. <hi>2</hi>
                        </note>Dum fierent tardâ dulcia poma morâ.</l>
                  </q> Not remembring his charge, loytered there till the fruite was ripe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> 33.</note> Nor yet like <hi>Noah's,</hi> which forgetting his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, buſied it ſelfe amongſt the putrified and rotten carkaſes of the ceaſing <hi>Deluge. Abraham</hi> will driue theſe from him; hee cannot endure their ſight: his ſeruants are principled ſo well, that they will taſte no meate till they haue deliuered their Meſſage.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This practiſe is erroneous, &amp; ſuch as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth with exceeding diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantage to the authors of the ſame. For it is avouched by an Oracle of diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, That he which ſendeth any weighty meſſages, by ſuch as are of weaker capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, cutteth off the feete, &amp; drinketh da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage. Pro. 26. verſ. 6. <hi>Tacit: hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor: lib.</hi> 2.</note>It is the nature of many in choyce of Inſtruments, to ſelect for their owne vſe and purpoſe, men of a plainer ſorte, and ſuch as without ſearching into the depth and qualitie of their deſignes, are able to doe what euer is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned them, &amp; when the buſineſſe is diſpatched, returne (without adding, or ſubtracting anie thing whereby to grace themſelues) a true &amp; faithful relation of the ſucceſſe.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19386:13"/> He muſt not therefore be like <hi>Otho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſoldiers, <hi>qui iuſſa du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum interpretari, quàm exequimalebant;</hi> who tooke delight to comment vpon the directions of their Leaders, rather then performe them: but without enquiring after the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſcope of his intent, or ſearching on what reaſons, motiues, &amp; inducements it is grounded, borne as it were <hi>Daed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lijs rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> as the <hi>Comike</hi> ſaith, vpon the wings of <hi>Daed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lus,</hi> cut through the midſt of all oppoſed interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and encumbrances whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>He muſt not alwaies diſcouer the full extent, and length of his reache, but in ſome caſes, <hi>caqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſcit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> ſeeme ignorant of what hee well conceiues eſpecially when he ſeeth his Patron is deſirous to haue them ſo cloſely carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that none may be acquainted with the ſubſtance, but himſelfe, and vſeth him but only as an inſtrument of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conueyance. When <hi>Tiberius</hi> with darke and doubtfull ſpeeches (as his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner was) did ſtil reiect the Empire from himſelfe, <hi>Patribus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Annal: lib: <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vnus metus ne intelligere vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derentur;</hi> the Senators were afraid of nothing more, then that he ſhould perceiue they vnderſtood him.</p>
               <p>Paſſion doth often-times miſleade the wiſeſt, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them reſolue in their diſtemperature vpon the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of many enterpriſes and attempts, which were they followed and archieued, could not but blacke and ſoyle the faireneſſe of their reputation. Now here it is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a faithfull and truſty ſeruant, howſoeuer hee come by the knowledge of ſuch vnripe determinations, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his owne diſcouery, or his Maiſters imparting, to oppoſe, and diuert him as much as may be from engaging himſelfe in ſuch proceedings, by letting him ſee the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards and in conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that may follow therevpon: and this be muſt doe, not by precept, but example; not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiuely, but by implication; and by bringing him in, as <hi>Nathan</hi> did the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> as a iudge,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam. c.</hi> 12.</note> to cenſure his own error in the perſon of a third; for feare an honeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction ſhould be reiected as a conſoriall taxation.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:19386:14"/>
               <p>Such as are eleuated in eſtates, and aduanced aboue the pitch of ordinary men, to places of dignitie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, can not endure to be controld in any thing. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes are harſh to them, and cleane againſt the haire. Whoſoeuer therefore would reforme them, he muſt not take the neerer way, but the ſafer, which is indeede by circumſtance, by bouts, and windings. For to come blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and directly to the point, might peraduenture inferre ſuſpicion of contempt, and want of due reſpect towards their perſon, in him that doth it, whereby their minds may be exaſperated and incenſed againſt him; whereas by fetching a little compaſſe, and by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demning their head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong and vnbridled courſes, or commending the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in others, not ſeeming to glance at any time at what is done by them, he may diſcharge his duty without feare of danger.<note place="margin">Plin. Sec. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Praecipere qualis eſſe debeat princeps, pulchrum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ſed oneroſum, ac prope ſuperbum eſt: laudare verò optimum Principem, ac per hoc posteris, velut è ſpecula lumen, quod ſequan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur oſtendere idem vtilitatis habet, arrogantiae nihil.</hi> It is a meanes whereby impatient Patients are oftentimes moſt happily recouered without cauterizing or inciſion. But if this ſofter oppoſition can worke within them no impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, let loue and dutifull regard embolden him againſt diſpleaſure; and rather then they ſhould periſh through their owne wilfulneſſe, let him confront them in a more open manner. <hi>Feri, ſed tamen audi;</hi> Strike me, but yet heare me, ſayd <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> to one of <hi>Lacedaemon,</hi> and ſo muſt he to them. His libertie of ſpeech in this, cannot but receiue from them in colder blood, a charitable and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſuch as may anſwere the lawfulneſſe of his intent and meaning; prouided alwayes, that ſome apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geticall excuſe tending to mitigation, doe either goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or follow after; informing them aright, that the boldneſſe of his reproofes and dehortations, proceeded from no other ground, then from a dutious and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant care he had of their ſecuritie. For otherwiſe he hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19386:14"/> himſelfe vpon the very inſtant, and that vainely, without any good effect at all.<note place="margin">Q. Curt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Witneſſe <hi>Charidemus</hi> the Athenian, whom <hi>Darius</hi> impatient of all truth, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for his honeſt counſaile to be ſlaine. Witneſſe alſo <hi>Caliſthenes,</hi> whom <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> tutor to <hi>Alexander</hi> the great,<note place="margin">Plutar. in Alex.</note> was wont to reprehend and admoniſh for his vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable freedome in this kinde towards his Soueraigne, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaging as it were vnto him the tragicall euent, which ſhortly after followed thereupon, by this verſe of <hi>Homer;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.<note place="margin">Iliad. lib. <hi>18.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Forbeare my ſonne ſuch round-ſpun talke to haue,</l>
                     <l>Or it will bring thee to a ſuddaine graue.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Witneſſe likewiſe <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and bleſſed <hi>Stephen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> 4. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. <hi>verſe</hi> 51.</note> with diuers others, to whom the like was alike diſaſtrous; though indeed I taxe it not in them as a deficiencie; for what they ſpake, was by the influence and inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt. I onely quote them as apparant prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of thoſe butcherous and tragicall <hi>Cataſtrophes,</hi> that enſue ſuch plainneſſe.</p>
               <p>In matters that are intricate and ambiguous, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his counſaile and aduiſe is asked, let him be wary how he doth proceed. For to vtter it as a Maxime, or poſition, whereby to equall the conceit and opinion of his Patron; or by way of Compariſon, whereby to weaken and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it, would peraduenture proue diſtaſtefull, and beget diſlike. In the diſſoluing therefore of ſuch knots, and doubts, let him abate and qualifie the ſtrength and vigor of his iudgement, with prudent limitations and cautions, and worke him, ſo he know it aſſuredly to be beſt, to a gentle acceptation of it, not by direct expreſſion, but ſlye inſinuation. For as <hi>Cobaris</hi> the Mede aduiſed <hi>Beſſus, Seruo vtilius eſt parere dicto, quàm afferre conſilium, quum illos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Q. Curt. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>qui pareant, idem quod caeteros maneat, qui verò ſuadeant, proprium periculum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſt of all, though he may ſhew himſelfe deſirous of imployment, and thinke it an honour likewiſe to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployd,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19386:15"/> yet muſt he not in any caſe voluntarily and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe make proffer of his ſeruice to him: for this were but to queſtion his authoritie, and doubt the power which he hath to command him. Aboue all, let him firſt in regard of himſelfe, beware he doe not thruſt and obtrude it on him, for feare acceptance ſhould be thought a ſufficient requitall. Secondly, that he obſerue a gradation in the diſcouerie of his abilities, and abſtaine from doing too much at once, for feare leaſt what is well done might not be throughly apprehended. Thirdly, that he feele not too ſoone the reward of his vertue, whether it be in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, honour, fauour, or applauſe: for if he ſeeme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with a penie, it will be thought a prodigall and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous thing to giue him a pound. Men ſhape and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion their liberalities according to the minds and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of thoſe, on whom they doe beſtow them. Let him take heed therefore that by ſeeming pleaſed with a little, he giue them not occaſion to ſuſpect, he was neuer vſed to more. Laſtly, that he doe not thruſt himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difference (whereby to publiſh and proclaime his owne deficiencies) into thoſe imployments, for which he is not proper:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Iuvenal. Sat. <hi>11.</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                        </note>— nec enim loricam poſcit Achillis</l>
                     <l>Therſites, in quaſe traducebat Vlyſſes.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It is not for a weaker then <hi>Milo</hi> to beare an Oxe, nor a leſſer then <hi>Atlas</hi> to vnderprop the heauens. For accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the other Satyriſt,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nauem ſi poſcat ſibi peronatus arator</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Luciferi rudis, exclamet</hi> Melicerta <hi>periſſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Frontem de rebus — Perſ. Sat.</hi> 5.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If for a Ship the hob-naild clowne ſhould call,</l>
                        <l>Which had no knowledge in the Starres at all,</l>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19386:15"/>
                        <l>Great <hi>Melicerta</hi> ſtreight wayes would exclame,</l>
                        <l>That earthly things were quite depriu'd of ſhame.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> refuſed the Armour of <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe he felt it cumberſome, and choſe that weapon to encounter his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie withall which beſt became his ſtrength and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They therefore which finde themſelues oppreſſed and ouercharged with a burthen,
<q>
                     <l>Abijciant potius, quàm quò perferre iubentur,<note place="margin">Hor. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>13.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ellas ſtulti impingant, Aſinaeque paternum</l>
                     <l>Cognomen vertant in riſum, &amp; fabula fiant.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. How to conuerſe in Court, and of the meanes whereby to purchaſe fauour, and ſtand ſecure from the manie <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which are there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to anie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Courte (ſaith one) is like a raging and tempeſtuous Sea:<note place="margin">Guarini, nelle lette.</note> their onely difference is this, that he which ſaileth well in the one, and he that doth ill in the other, arriueth in the end with ſafety to his wiſht-for Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. That which is elſe-where honoured as a Vertue, is hated heere (ſaith he) as a defect. <hi>Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> is cleane excluded from amongſt them, and ſimple <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> is had in no eſteeme. To ſpeake without feyning, to loue without flattering, are counted arguments of a baſe and ſluggiſh diſpoſition. But let vs imagine that this being vttered farre beyond the <hi>Alpes</hi> was meant but onely to the <hi>Florentine,</hi> and comming neerer home, conſider a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19386:16"/> while the words of <hi>Aretine,</hi> to <hi>Francis</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning certaine Cardinalls and Biſhops that did attend his <hi>Louvre. Vorrei</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>che la bugia campeggiaſſe nella mia bocca come fà la verità in quella del Clero.</hi> O that a lye could ſtumble in my mouth, as truth it ſelfe doth in the mouth of the Cleargie. Now where the ſalte is ſo vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uory, how can any thing be ſeaſoned? Yet here with vs, if either imitation or patternes of Gods diuine and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary goodneſſe had any power to reframe the mindes of men, wee ſhould not neede to be afraide of ſuch enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. We haue a Soueraigne, that groundeth not the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of his Crowne vpon the teares and ſighes of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Hee hates that gardener worſe then <hi>Alexander,</hi> that cutteth his hearbs vp by the roote;<note place="margin">Plutarch. in Alex: Sueton: in Tibe:</note> and with <hi>Tiberius, Tondere mavult pecus quàm degl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bere.</hi> His wiſedome in the placing of his fauours and liberalities, exempteth him from the number of thoſe weaker Princes, whom <hi>Crates</hi> likened vnto figtrees that grewe vppon ſome craggy and rocky clifts, whoſe fruite none can approach, or taſte of, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kites and Rauens. In a word, he is as abſolutely good, as we account him great; as fully milde, as wee account him mightie; as well renowmed for mercie, as for maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: ſo that as <hi>Plinie</hi> the ſecond reported of <hi>Traian,</hi> there remaineth nothing to the accompliſhing of our felicitie, <hi>Sed vt Dij Caeſarem imitentur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Panegyr. Traia.</note> that the Gods would follow him, and continue as fauourable and propitious Lords to vs, as he hath bene.</p>
               <p>Thoſe vertues which only by good diſcipline and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation are bred in others, were borne with him; there is nothing within the compaſſe of his Imperiall boſome, that is eyther borrowed or feyned. Beſides, there are many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that attend his Princely perſon, ſo wiſe and heedfull in the effecting of their purpoſes; ſo honeſt and religious in the performance of their promiſes; that their wordes and actions, are euen the precepts, and precedents of true Moralitie. But as in heauen amidſt the Angels, and in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19386:16"/> ſight of God himſelfe, there haue bene <hi>Lucifers;</hi> ſo I wiſh that in the circuite of great <hi>Britaines</hi> Court, there were not likewiſe ſome, who notwithſtanding the benefite of ſuch examples, led by the inſtigation of their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted &amp; depraued wills, run headlong on in many myery courſes, and are conſcious to themſelues, if not of worſe, at leaſt of thoſe fore-named imputations: Some that care not, ſo they purchaſe profite to themſelues,<note place="margin">Actaeone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comedent iſti canes.</note> at what exceſsiue rate they ſell the Princes breath, to the poore needy ſuppliant, nor with what vaine delayes they torture mens expectations, in hope of further Fees; Some that hauing drunke of <hi>Machiauel's</hi> impure and troubled ſtreames, care not ſo much for Vertue it ſelf, as for the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhewe and apparance thereof, becauſe they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, That the credite of it is a helpe, but the vſe of it a hinderance.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <hi>Pulchra Lauerna</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Da mihi fallere, da iuſto ſancto<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> videri;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hor. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>16.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Noctem peccatis, &amp; fraudibus obijce nubem.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Deigne ſweete Protectreſſe of the Theeuiſh kinde,</l>
                     <l>I may beguile, yet ſeeme a Sainte in minde:</l>
                     <l>Shade my offences with a vaile of Night,</l>
                     <l>And let a miſt keepe my deceits from light.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Weakeneſſe of <hi>Vnderstanding</hi> is thought the ground of <hi>Honeſtie;</hi> and <hi>Vpright-dealing,</hi> the way to <hi>Beggerie.</hi> But let not him, <hi>quem Titan finxit meliore luto,</hi> be tainted with theſe impurities, or worke for the more compendious rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his Fortunes, vpon ſuch diſpenſations fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rules of Charitie and Integritie. Let him thinke it a iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Vt fumo pereat, qui fumum vendit;</hi> and not doe anything, whereby his ſoule may become obnoxious to thoſe helliſh Furies, which attend the authors of vnlawfull practiſes. Let him not flatter himſelfe with any
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19386:17"/> hope, that what he doth may happily be concealed; for this indeede is but a meere deluſion. There is continually a God within vs, ſaith the Stoike, there is an Angell ſtill about vs,<note place="margin">Epict. in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertat. ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rri. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and what neede of any light haue theſe to looke into the nature of our actions? Let no man therefore proſtitute his voyce for a ſmall quantitie of glittering droſſe to baſe Vniuſtice, nor teach his hands according to the vſuall faſhion to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine a bribe, towards the impugning of an honeſt cauſe.<note place="margin">Plaut. in Aſinar.</note> Theſe <hi>oculatae manus,</hi> which as the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ike ſayth, <hi>quod vident, credunt,</hi> are fitter in a houſe of brothelrie, then in a place of dignitie. But who ſo looſeneth the raines to ſuch impieties, let him know, that he cannot poſſibly leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, or extenuate his fault with any faire pretences of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. For it is otherwiſe in ours, then it was in the Court of <hi>Vitellius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſtor. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> where, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> records, <hi>probitate, aut induſtria nemo certauit,</hi> no man in competitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any publike charge did euer alleage either his honeſtie, or induſtrie, whereby to purchaſe it; <hi>vnum ad potentiam iter, prodigis epulis &amp; ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, ſaginaque ſatiare inexplebiles Vitellij libidines:</hi> the onely way to greatneſſe, was by bankettings, and prodigall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, as likewiſe by cramming the vnſatiable longings and deſires of <hi>Vitellius.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>— Exeat aulâ</l>
                  <l>Qui velit eſſe pius—</l>
               </q>
               <p>is an Axiome, which in this place hath no place at all. Such is the benignitie of our Prince, ſuch now the ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our times, that Vertue neede not any longer be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to lay aſide her habit of diſguiſe, or doubt thoſe ſcandalous appeales, indictments, and delations, which in former ages haue beene framed and preferred againſt her, by the enuious ſpirits of malitious perſons, to the ſupplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of an able worth. Goodneſſe with vs is not a thing in queſtion, witneſſe examples that approue it, and the lawes which do exact it.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19386:17"/>
                  <l>Iam fides, &amp; pax, &amp; honor,<note place="margin">Horat. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pod. lib.</note> pudorque</l>
                  <l>Priſcus, &amp; neglecta redire Virtus</l>
                  <l>Audet.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Wherefore howſoeuer a round and iuſt proceeding may peraduenture be deſpiſed of a few, who out of Charitie (if I may profane the word) to the prince of darkneſſe, as men intending peraduenture to enlarge his empire and dominions, endeauour, as much as in them lyeth, to faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery one to their owne mould, and make them as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted and prodigious in their life and conuerſation as themſelues, let no man notwithſtanding, ſuffer himſelfe to be diuerted from any laudable and ſpecious courſe, but whether he thriue by it or no (as this is commonly the let and oppoſition, by which mens minds are deviated often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from what is good) goe on in it with an euen paſe, and conſtant reſolution, rather to vndergoe with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence what accidents ſoeuer can befall him, then to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the practiſe of any ſiniſter and vnlawfull arts. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but redound vnto him in the end with great aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
               <q>Virtus ipſa ſibi pretium, nihil indiga laudis.<note place="margin">Claudian.</note>
               </q>
               <p>The Spirit of Truth in the mouth of Wiſedome hath preached to the hearts of men, <hi>That vprightneſſe ſhall keepe the innocent in his way,</hi> Pro. 13.6. and withall, <hi>That the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull man ſhall not roſt that which he takes in hunting.</hi> Pro. 12. verſe 27.</p>
               <p>But I feare I haue too long inſiſted vpon this; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the Readers better ſatisfaction, I will reduce the remainder of this head into as ſtreight a roome as poſſibly I may.</p>
               <p>If in the Court (as gawdie ignorance is no where elſe more inſolent then there) he be offered any wrongs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities and affronts, by men of greater power, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher out-ſides then himſelfe, let him either not thinke
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19386:18"/> vpon them, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did, who, as <hi>Tullie</hi> witneſſeth, had ſo excellent a memorie, that he ſeldome forgot any thing but iniuries and diſgraces; or let him ſlight both them and their authors, as <hi>Cato</hi> did, who when a fellow ſtrooke him on the mouth, would ſeeme to take no notice either of him, or of his fact; or thirdly, let him diſſemble them, and with <hi>Antigonus</hi> winke at many things he both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and ſeeth.<note place="margin">De Ira. li. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> For according to <hi>Seneca, Multae iniuriae nos tranſeunt, ex quibus pleraſque non accepit, qui neſcit:</hi> or laſt of all, let him with <hi>Socrates</hi> conuert and turne them to a ieſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Circumſcribenda multis modis ira eſt;</hi> Anger, ſaith the ſame Philoſopher, is to be circumſcribed in diuers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: <hi>Pleraque in luſum, iocumque vertantur;</hi> Moſt things are to be made rather a matter of ſport and laughter, then of any diſcontent. For as <hi>Cremutius Cordus</hi> auouched in his defence before <hi>Tiberius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tacit. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſpreta exoleſcunt, ſin iraſcaris agnita videntur;</hi> being lightly ſet by, they doe ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vaniſh; if thou ſtomacke them, they ſeeme to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged. But if he perceiue they preſume vpon his ſufferance, and by reaſon of his too much ſoftneſſe and facilitie of nature, make him the onely ſubiect of their ſcornes, let him aſſume vnto himſelfe a more fortified kind of carriage, and with ſome ſhew of edge and ſpirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front their daring impudencie; prouided alwayes they be not men, whoſe hye-built fortunes too much ouerlooke his owne. For then he will finde it more conuenient to proceede according to the former directions, then by ſuch violent, and open courſes redeeme himſelfe from baſe indignities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19386:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. Of the manner how to conuerſe with ſtrangers, in forraine Regions, whereby to profite our ſelues, and benefite our Countrey.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch as are imploy'd in matters of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſie, &amp; forraine treaties, muſt labour (that they may the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſe with men in nature &amp; diſpoſition differing from themſelues) to be throughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the wiſedome of <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> which conſiſteth onely in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and perfect knowledge of thoſe precedent humours, cuſtomes, and inclinations, to which we muſt accommodate and conforme our owne.</p>
               <p>Diſtance in manners, breedes difference in mindes: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>Vonones,</hi> who by the appointment of <hi>Tiberius</hi> being inſtituted and ordained king ouer the <hi>Parthians,</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained amongſt them at the firſt with ſingular appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and applauſe, <hi>vt ferme ad noua imperia;</hi> according to the vſuall faſhion of an vnſteady multitude, vpon any change or alteration of gouernment: but after they had once obſerued the diſſimilitude and diſproportion which was betweene themſelues and him,<note place="margin">Tacit: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib: <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> and found that he was a man as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports, <hi>diuerſus a maiorum inſtitutis, rarò venatu, ſegni equorum cura, faſtu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> erga patrias epulas,</hi> whoſe aduerſe courſes did ſeeme to contradict the cuſtomes of their anceſtors, being no way giuen to thoſe ſportes and paſtimes wherein themſelues delighted, they did vttterly diſtaſte him. And vpon this, or the like examples, did <hi>C. Caeſar</hi> peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ground that imitation of his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19386:19"/> ſonne, ſent <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archits</hi> to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> who meeting there with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> did ſeeke by proffering him his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, to reconcile himſelfe vnto him; and when the Prince (whether to try if his reuolt were onely feined, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon any other more priuate touch, which might concerne himſelfe) did vpbraide him thereupon with foule ingratitude towards <hi>Dauid,</hi> alleaging many ſpeciall fauours he had receiued at his hands, and how from time to time he had beene honoured by him with a moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and ſingular affection; faſhioned with all humilitie, according to the directions which he receiued at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from his Soueraigne,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam. cap.</hi> 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</note> this wiſe reply; <hi>Whome the Lord and this people, and all the men of Iſrael haue choſen for a Prince and leader, to goe in and out before them, his will I bee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and with him onely will I dwell; Yea, looke what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and ſeruice I haue hitherto performed to him, the like with more dutious reſpect will I henceforth render vnto thee.</hi> And through this dexterous application of himſelfe vnto him, he preuaild ſo farre, that by diſcouering the plots and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of <hi>Ahithopel,</hi> he confounded them, ſecur'd his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, ſau'd his Maiſter. So that if we rightly weigh and conſider the perſons of the author and the actor of this buſineſſe, together with the reaſons, motiues, and incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon which it was grounded, and obſerue withall, that the Lord himſelfe hath no way taxed it in his holy and bleſſed word of any blemiſh, lameneſſe, or deficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as he did thoſe irregular and ſinfull actions of his, which are there mentioned, and enrolled; but hath ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam. cap.</hi> 17. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</note> as appeareth by the text, expreſſed himſelfe to be a fauourer and furtherer of it; I doe not ſee how any man can iuſtly cenſure, and condemne it, as vnlawfull, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the life of either might be thought worthy to be bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with any marke of ignominie &amp; reproch. For, as I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, there is a difference betweene a publike Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, and a priuate Familie, where Vertue is to ſhew her ſelfe alwayes in her owne likeneſſe, without any maske or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19386:19"/> habit of deluſion; whereas in the other, vnleſſe I erre and faile in my accounts, ſhe may change hir cloathes,<note place="margin">Verè ſapiens non ſe in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quibus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, ſed aptat. <hi>And ſuch a one was</hi> Piſo. Tacit. Annal. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; Lepidus. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> if not diſguiſe her countenance; and, ſo ſhe direct &amp; intend her courſe to the ſame goale, run right or byas as ſhe ſeeth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. But I will ſtep from hence vnto an other point, which is to be obſerued in this example, and that is this, <hi>That the dutie which we owe vnto our King and Countrie, muſt alwayes be preſerued and maintained with more religion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, then either life or being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is infuſed and formed in all things a two-fold imitation or propenſion to what is good: the one, as euery particular is a <hi>Totall,</hi> and eſſentiall ſubſtance of it ſelfe; the other, as it is a ſubordinate part or member to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter body, as appeareth plainely in thoſe maſſier Elements, which of their firſt and inbred forme doe make the center of the earth the onely period of their motion; yet rather then nature ſhould ſuffer any divulſion, interruption, or diſturbance in the progreſſe and continuance of her courſe, the water, we ſee, forſaketh the center, to which of it ſelfe it ſtandeth affectionate and inclinable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that inherent propertie of weightie bodies, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpwards to relieue the world. In a man, vnleſſe he will belye the author of his creation, through his degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and baſe proceedings, it is expreſſed and ſet out in a farre fairer Character.<note place="margin">Rom. cap. <hi>9.</hi> verſe <hi>3.</hi> Exod. cap. <hi>32.</hi> verſ. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſireth to be anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized for his brethren; and <hi>Moſes</hi> when the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> through their Idolatrous defection, had in a terrible and fearfull manner incenſed the Lord of hoaſts againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, becommeth an humble ſuter in their behalfe, vnto his heauenly Maieſtie, deſiring him, that hee would cauſe his mercie to be knowne, in the free pardon and remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſinnes: if not, that he would vouchſafe to raſe his name out of thoſe rolles and regiſters of Immortality, which he himſelfe had written. Yea, the very Heathens haue eleuated and exalted this good which is communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiue, aboue the thought of any priuate or particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19386:20"/> Witneſſe that memorable ſpeech of <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, who (when he was in Commiſſion of purueyance for a dearth and ſcarſitie at <hi>Rome</hi>) being earneſtly diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his friends from hazarding himſelfe vpon the Sea in ſo rough a ſeaſon, controlled their faint and crauen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations with this reply,<note place="margin">Plut. Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theg.</note> 
                  <hi>Vt eam, non vt viuam neceſſe eſt:</hi> It is neceſſarie that I ſhould goe, but not that I ſhould liue; and ſo ſet foote into the ſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tull. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Offic.</note>
                  <hi>Omnium ſocietatum nulla eſt grauior, nulla carior, quàm ea, quae cum Repub. eſt vnicuique noſtrûm. Cari ſunt parentes, cari liberi, propinqui, familiares; ſed omnes omnium caritates patria vna complexa eſt, pro qua quis bonus dubitet mortem oppetere, ſi ei ſit profuturus?</hi> Of all ſocieties and combinations there is none ſo weightie, as that which conſiſteth betweene the Common-wealth, and euery home-borne Indiuiduall. Our Parents are deare, our Children deare, our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and acquaintance deare; but all this deareneſſe our Countrie deriueth wholly to it ſelfe, for whoſe aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and commoditie no good or loyall Patriot will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be afraid, ſaith <hi>Tullie,</hi> to abandon and forſake his life. The ſafetie of our King muſt be preferred before the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our neereſt kinne. So that our Agent, as an honeſt and faithfull ſubiect, muſt alwayes, but eſpecially in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine regions, where there is, hath beene, or in time may be any hoſtile difference (as the leagues of loue and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betweene Princes are not alwayes of long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) ſo faſhion and conforme his carriage, that the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the publike weale maybe the onely marke and ſcope of his endeauours.</p>
               <p>He muſt labour to get good information of ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars as lye within the compaſſe of that Clime, in which hee doth reſide; as namely, of the ſituation of the place, the nature and diſpoſition of the people; their lawes, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, ſtatutes, and decrees; their manner of gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well <hi>Oeconomicall</hi> as <hi>Politicall;</hi> their forces and reuenues; their friendes, factions, and allyes; and from
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19386:20"/> thence deſcend to a diligent ſuruey of all Eſtates &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions by themſelues, quoting in euery determinate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of more honoured ranke, his rules, his principles, and obſeruations; his deſires, endes, and actions; laſt of all, his oppoſites, fautors, and competitors. For if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards occaſion of enter-courſe befall him with any ſuch, hee ſhall by this meanes knowe how to contriue, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, conduct, and manage the buſineſſe to his beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage.</p>
               <p>In compaſſing the firſt there is no difficulty, if in the choyce of his acquaintance, hee fit himſelfe with ſuch as are familiar and conuerſant with thoſe that looke into the world, and are likewiſe generally wel intelligenced them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in euery ſeueral kinde: &amp; as for the laſt, it may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily effected, by getting priuacie &amp; inwardnes with their enemies, friendes, or ſeruants, which indeed doe likely report them trueſt of anie. For the malice of the firſt will peraduenture aggrauate and make worſe their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, faultes, and weakeneſſes; the affection of the ſecond too highly prize, it may be, their good deſeruings, vertues, and abilities: whereas the laſt are quickly drawne and wonne, by thoſe that are familiar with them, to make a perfect and exact delineation both of their worth and wants, diſcourſing of the one with ſignes of ioy and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full approbation; of the other with ſhewes of griefe and ſad commiſeration.</p>
               <p>But if he would vnderſtand their inclination from their owne diſcouery, and knowe by ſounding how well affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they are vnto their owne eſtabliſhed gouernement, if when need required they might not bee wrought to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond &amp; aſſiſt his Soueraigne, in any enterpriſe or attempt that might be to his profit and aduantage, he were better proceede by way of argument and reaſoning, then direct enquiry. It is a courſe of greater certainty, of more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity; and ſuch as with no ſmall aduantage and ſucceſſe was practiſed by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> who intending the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19386:21"/> depoſition of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and hauing therevpon inuited to a ſupper certaine of their friends, did ſet on foote the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of <hi>killing an Vſurper and a Tyrant,</hi> with no other intent, then to collect and gather by the iudiciall and definitiue arreſt of each, which of the number preſent, might beſt be made aſſociates with them in the buſineſſe: Or laſt of all, he may follow the example of <hi>Germanicus,</hi> who when the time was come, that his armie ſhould confront the forces of <hi>Arminius,</hi> conſidered with himſelfe in what manner he might come beſt to knowe, how well prepared and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued his ſoldiers were for that aſſault. He knew it was the faſhion of the Tribunes and Centurions, <hi>Laeta ſaepius quàm comperta nuntiare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tacit: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib: <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> to relate matters of gladnes rather then of truth: Hee knew that his <hi>Liberti</hi> were of a baſe and ſeruile diſpoſition; that friends would rather flatter then informe; laſt of all, he was not ignorant, that if hee ſhould commaund a meeting and a congregation to bee called, whatſoeuer were vttered there by the voyces of a fewe, would in an inſtant be confirmed by the conſenting cryes, and ſuffrages of all; and therefore in the ende he ſetled his ſuſpenſion vpon this concluſion, <hi>penitus noſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das mentes, cum ſecreti, &amp; incuſtoditi, inter militares cibos, ſpem aut metum proferrent;</hi> That the onely meanes to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their mindes, was to obſerue and marke them, when being priuate, and vnlook't to, amidſt their military fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and refections, they freely vented both their hopes and feares; and therevpon hee cloathed himſelfe in an vnknowne diſguiſe, and went vnto their Tents, where he diſcouered to the full their loue to him, their longing for the Combat; whil'ſt one extolled the nobleneſſe of his birth, an other the comelineſſe of his perſon; moſt of them his patience, his mildneſſe, his immutable and conſtant minde in all things, whether light or ſerious; all of them acknowledging that in the battaile they would manifeſt their gratefulnes vnto him, by ſacrificing thoſe perfidious violaters and breakers of the peace, to Glory &amp; Reuenge.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19386:21"/> So that our Agent, for the procuring of better informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may now and then reſort to places of publike meetings. For heere it is that men doe often ſet aſide their grauitie, and being in the height of all their iollitie, doe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or at leaſt vpon the leaſt occaſion lay open as it were the fences and incloſures of their boſomes: And hence it was, the ancient Greekes would by no meanes ſuffer any in their company at ſuch aſſemblies, that would not faſhion themſelues vnto the reſt: their ordinary word of entertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, drink, or get thee gone; to the intent, that nothing of whatſoeuer was done or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken amongſt them in their wine, might be climinated, or ſo much as thought vpon, by any then preſent, the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe following. They counted them no fit companions for themſelues in their looſe and freer recreations, that did altogether ouer-whelme, and drowne their memories in the cup: as appeareth by <hi>Martiall</hi> in an Epigramme of his, compoſed againſt <hi>Procillus,</hi> on the like occaſion.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Heſterna nocte tibi dixeramus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quincunces puto poſt decem peractos,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram.</hi> 28.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Coenares hodie Procille mecum.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu factam tibi rem ſtatim putaſti,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et non ſobria verba ſubnotaſti,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Exemplo nimium periculoſo.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>Laſt night, my friend, when I did raſhly ſay,</l>
                     <l>After Canary cups had drown'd my wit,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Procillus</hi> thou ſhalt ſup with me to day;</l>
                     <l>Thou thoughtſt, thou hadſt a prettie perquiſit;</l>
                     <l>And taking notice of my drunken words,</l>
                     <l>Gau'ſt ill example by ſuch obſeruation.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Procille,</hi> I loathe the mate, whoſe thought records</l>
                     <l>A table-tale breath'd in vnſober paſſion.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19386:22"/>
               <p>findeth, that theſe doe farre exceede the former, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine from altering any thing of whatſoeuer is appointed him: but if on the other ſide, the benefit outwey the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, I ſee no reaſon why he may not (like wiſer Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, that will not ſtick to venter a little when there is any hope at all of gayning much) ſomewhat decline from the preciſe and ſtrict <hi>Mandamus</hi> of his prime and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall <hi>Motor,</hi> to follow that which in his owne diſcourſe and iudgement he apprehendeth to be far more probable. Yet euen in this I will aduiſe him to haue reſpect vnto the nature and diſpoſition of him, to whom he doth retaine, and gouerne both himſelfe and all his actions continually thereafter; becauſe if there be in him that ſowerneſſe and ſeuereneſſe, which is found in many, I would not wiſh him to alter in any point or circumſtance the forme and order which is ſet him downe, for feare leaſt that ſhould happen vnto him, which befell, as hiſtories report, a certain Engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Athens,</hi> to whom <hi>P. Craſſus Mutianus,</hi> during his reſidence in <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſent for the greater of the two Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſts which he had ſeene in <hi>Athens,</hi> to make a Ramme thereof, wherewith to batter downe the walles of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine towne which he intended to aſſault. The Enginer as one well vnderſtood in matters of that nature, knew that the greater was no way fit for ſuch a purpoſe; and becauſe the leſſer might beſt be carryed, and was moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for his turne, he ſent him that. But <hi>Mutianus</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing how the buſineſſe went, commaunded inſtantly he ſhould be brought before him, and without admittance of excuſes, cauſed him to be ſo cruelly puniſhed for his diſobedience, that he dyed. To perſons therefore ſo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere and ſterne, he muſt be alwayes wonderfull reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue. They abhorre to be counſailed, when they deſire to be obeyed.</p>
               <p>It happeneth oftentimes, that in ſome caſes, <hi>Fieri</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture may bee vtterly condemned, when <hi>Factum est,</hi> may be approoued and commended; as did appeare by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19386:22"/> 
                  <hi>Pompey,</hi> when the Pirate <hi>Moenas</hi> came vnto him, whil'ſt <hi>Antonie</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> vpon his inuitation, were feaſting in his Gallies, and ſaid, <hi>Wilt thou that I cut the cables, and in one inſtant make thee Lorde of all the Romane Empire? Thou ſhould'ſt haue done it,</hi> anſwered hee, <hi>and not haue tolde me of it, now let vs content our ſelues with what we haue; for as for me, I neuer learnt to falſifie my faith to any man, or ſeeke my owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in his ouerthrowe, by acting or conſenting to diſloyall treaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> So that here he may proceede without direction, if his conceite and apprehenſion can out of the nature and quality of the action, rightly conſider the concluſion. There are many that could wiſh in the diſtemperature of their paſſions ſome things were done, which if they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to bee done, as <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> can neuer want thoſe that will ſeeke to ſatisfie her baſeſt appetites, they doe for euer abhorre the preſence of the doer; and would not,<note place="margin">Saul hath no ſooner ſpoke the word, but Doegs weapon is in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells of the Prieſts.</note> if it were poſſible, retaine one thought of him, or of his deede. <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> could not endure to looke vpon the head of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor, nor yet vpon <hi>Theodotus</hi> that did preſent it to him: And <hi>Alexander</hi> condemned <hi>Beſſus</hi> for the like, to a ſeuerer torture. He muſt be therefore very wary what he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam: c.</hi> 22</note> and haue a ſpeciall care that the performance of it may not bee preiudiciall either to him or to his maiſter. <hi>Miniſtri ſcelerum tanquàm exprobra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ab ipſis authoribus ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per aspiciuntur.</hi> They ſee in them as it were by reflection,<note place="margin">Tacit: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: lib: <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> the foule corruption of their owne depraued will, which makes them loath and deteſt the very ſight of them. He muſt not therefore be careleſſe of that which hee attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, but with all diligent attention ſee that it be no way repugnant to the lawes of God or Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19386:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. What literature and knowledge is required in a man, for the better enabling him to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe all kindes of buſineſſes whatſoeuer, <hi>and effect them with ſucceſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He imployments of a publike man are of ſundry kindes; &amp; ſometimes in the behalfe of his Prince, ſometimes of himſelfe, hee is to negotiate with men of ſeuerall callings and profeſſions. Firſt therefore I thinke it meete hee ſhould haue paſt through all the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Pawnes of <hi>Secular</hi> and <hi>diuine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> not parting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (as Merchants vſually from faires, whoſe repaire thither, was onely to learne the price of things) till ſuch time as he hath purchaſed to himſelf ſome ornament or other. He muſt taſte of all kinde of literature in generall, but make the ancient Regiſters of former ages his mindes more ordinary foode;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad.</hi> 1.</note> in which ſaith <hi>Liuie, Hoc praecipuè ſalubre ac frugiferum, omnis eum exempli documenta in illuſtri poſita intuêri, inde ſibi, ſuae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Reipub: quod imitetur, capiat; inde foedum inceptu, foedum exitu quod vitet.</hi> They will ſerue him for a <hi>Tutor</hi> in his priuate life, and for a <hi>Guide,</hi> in his publike actions.<note place="margin">Plut: in Timol.</note> For in them, concerning the firſt, he may, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as by a glaſſe, compoſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion his owne life, according to thoſe vertues that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in others. And concerning the laſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Rhetor: cap:</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Thoſe writings, wherein the Arts of men are regiſtred, are as the Arçenalls and ſtore-houſes of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike directions. For by the knowledge of things paſt we learne how to manage things preſent, and how to diſpoſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19386:23"/> of things that are to come. And indeed hee that is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnacquainted with the ſtate of thoſe times, which were long before Time had any eſtate in him, I eſteem him no other then an Infant, whoſe diſcurſiue facultie neuer trauailed beyond the arches of his cradle: for though his bodie be aged, yet his wit is childiſh, as being wholly deſtitute of experience, and vnexerciſed in the courſe of worldly affaires.<note place="margin">Polyb: lib: <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> And therfore <hi>Polybius</hi> did not raſhly and without mature deliberation tearme this hiſtoricall kinde of learning, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the trueſt diſcipline, exerciſe, and inſtitution, by which men may bee trained and brought vp to ciuill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Hiſtorie therefore (I meane) both ancient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne, muſt of neceſſity be one part, and that not the leaſt of his ſtudie. <hi>x. x. x.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Ciuill lawe</hi> muſt likewiſe be an other: though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſo accurate a knowledge in this as in the former, is not abſolutely required, yet a meane is neceſſarily deſired. Many groſſe and palpable errors haue iſſued in matters of treaty from the ignorance of Embaſſadors and their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in this profeſſion. In confirmation whereof, I will alleage that which hapned long ſince to the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> who ſent their Agents to yeelde themſelues to the mercie of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and to beſeech the Senat, not to ſuffer one of the faireſt Townes of the world, and the pride and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their victories to bee vnworthily waſted: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all which, what by reaſon of the facilitie of the Porte, the factious and tumultuous nature of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the fyering of it was for the preuenting of future com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtions throughly agreed vpon: And after that, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors were admitted, who receiuing (as they thought) an anſwere then which themſelues could not haue framed a better for their contentment, which was,<note place="margin">Appian: lib: de bello Pun:</note> 
                  <hi>That they ſhould retaine their Citie, with all the Rightes, Vſufruites, Charters, Liberties, Priuiledges, Immunities, &amp; Prerogatiues, which thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto they had enioyed,</hi> return'd home with great ioy &amp; glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19386:24"/> But alas, it was but a Meteor, that ſuddenly faded. For preſently after, the charge of effecting their former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, was by Commiſſion delegated to the younger <hi>Scipio:</hi> who haſtening towards <hi>Africa</hi> with a great Nauie, ſent <hi>Cenſormus</hi> to receiue of them their Ships, and three hundreth Hoſtages: which done, he commanded all the inhabitants of <hi>Carthage</hi> to auoyde, and prouide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues an habitation ſomewhat more diſcoaſted from the Porte then it; whereat (all aſtonied) they began to ſhewe how the Senate had aſſured them the ſafety of their City: wherevnto replie was made, That the faith which had bin giuen them, ſhould not bee violated in the leaſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but that their Citie was not tyed to the place, or to the walles of <hi>Carthage;</hi> which though it ſeeme a kinde of ſophyſticall proceeding, yet had it <hi>Lawe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> to authorize it.</p>
               <p>The word <hi>Citie,</hi> is a tearme that implyeth not any lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call place, as doth the word <hi>Towne,</hi> which the Latins call <hi>vrh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m ab vrb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratro;</hi> becauſe, as <hi>Varro</hi> ſaith, the circuite, and pourpris of Townes was wont to be traced out with Plough; but it ſignifieth the right vniting and incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſundry perſons and families into one bodie, vnder one iuſt and lawfull kinde of Politie; ſo that the Citie may be ſayd ſometimes to forſake the Towne. <hi>Non eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parietibus Respub.</hi> ſayd <hi>Pompey,</hi> when after he had drawne from <hi>Rome</hi> two hundreth Senators, and ſuch as were there beſides of any credit, or eſteeme, he left the walls to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Thus then were the poore inhabitants conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to abandon their towne to the will and pleaſure of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> who perhaps had neuer had it ſo good cheape, had their Embaſſadors ſooner vnderſtood the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene <hi>Towne</hi> and <hi>Citie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is the like fault in the treatie made betweene the two Cantons of <hi>Berne,</hi> and <hi>Friburgh,</hi> in the yeare one thouſand fiue hundreth and fiue, where by the ſecond article it is agreed, that, The league betweene both Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19386:24"/> ſhall remaine for euer, and as long as the walls of either towne ſhall endure. Many other fearefull and dangerous falls haue at ſundry times hapned vnto ſuch as haue neglected the benefit of ſo ſure a ſtay; and that with no leſſe danger to their Countrie, then diſcredit to themſelues. Wherefore I hold a ſuperficiall knowledge herein at the leaſt, to be neceſſarily required in one of publike place, that both at home and abroade he may be the better able to maintaine his own credit, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſafetie.</p>
               <p>A readie skilfulneſſe in neighbour-languages is an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, that cannot any way be wanting in him; the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining therefore of ſome perfection in them, muſt of force be made a part of his practiſe. He ſhall haue occaſion oftentimes to negotiate with ſtrangers: to whom without theſe aydes he cannot well impart himſelf, but with much doubt and inconueniencie.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, he muſt be very carefull, that whilſt he ſeemeth a Patriot abroade, he be not thought a ſtranger heere at home. To talke of forraine nations, and in ſome long and weariſome diſcourſe to relate their manners and their Cuſtomes, without ſome knowledge of his owne, is but as idle Chat; and cannot be taken, but as the ſymptome of a weake and crazie minde. The vſe of theſe things is only but for application: they ought not to be followed any farther then they can further vs in the vnderſtanding of our owne. Let him labour therefore with all diligence in the hiſtories of the kingdome in which he liueth, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the lawes, decrees, and ſtatutes of the ſame; that hauing out of them diſcouered the nature and condition of the people, the ſituation of the Countrie, and how and in what manner it is gouerned, he may the better imploy all other learning for his beſt aduantage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19386:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX. Of Negotiation in generall: wherein the ſeuerall Characters of mens natures are largely</hi> deſcribed; and the meanes by which to negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate with all ſorts of perſons, is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the full.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll practiſe conſiſteth either in working or diſcouering: the laſt I haue alreadie touched; and therefore here I will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alleage (to ſhew that howſoeuer it be not, becauſe it is of Indiuiduals, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed vnder precept, the knowledge of it may be poſſible) that which the light of true Moralitie hath aſſured vs; who ſayth in the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of the Prouerbs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 20. <hi>verſe</hi> 5.</note> verſ. 5. <hi>That the counſaile in the heart of man is like deepe waters, but he that hath vnderſtanding will draw it out.</hi> And as for the firſt, I vnderſtand thereby, that forcible application of perſuaſiue arguments and allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by which the parties with whom he doth negotiate, are incited and induced to giue him a full and perfect ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in all his demaunds; which may be eaſily effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, if that which he propoundeth, haue any reference to ſome wiſhed for obiect of the Appetite or Will: which as it is referred vnto the end that man deſireth, differeth from that inferiour naturall deſire, in that it looketh after nothing, but what Reaſon and Vnderſtanding, or the ſhew of Reaſon doth preſcribe; whereas the other is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mooued, or delighted, but onely with that good, which is ſenſible and apparant. For all other goodneſſe whatſoeuer, doth but weakely prouoke it; and therefore many things are neglected, which are moſt pretious, only becauſe themſelues are, as it were, the graues and ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of their owne worth and value.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19386:25"/>
               <p>Men are hardly wrought to any thing, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit not to be either good, profitable, or pleaſant. He muſt of neceſſitie therefore make theſe the grounds of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion; and hauing formerly obſerued the humours, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and inclinations of his Auditors, apply them with ſuch fitneſſe in regard of Circumſtance, that when he ſpeaketh, his diſcourſe may ſeeme in all things to anſwere their deſire, and be generally accepted, approued, and embraced, without examination, diſcuſſion, or oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Suae quiſque inuentionifauet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plin. Sec. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; quaſi fortiſſimum amplecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quum ab alio dictum eſt, quod ipſe praeuidit.</hi> And therefore, <hi>Omnibus dandum eſt aliquid, quod teneant, quod agnoſcant:</hi> which that he may the better doe, he muſt endeauour as much as in him lyeth, to haue a ſound and perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſeuerall Characters and tempers of mens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and diſpoſitions; as likewiſe of thoſe impreſſions which are impoſed vpon the minde, by the Sexe, by the Age, by the Climate, by the good or euill Conſtitution of the body, and the like, which are inherent, and Coevall with the ſubſtance: againe, thoſe, which are accidentall, and haue their originall but from the forme and ſhape of outward fortune; for all men are not to be wonne alike.</p>
               <p>The younger ſort are both incontinent &amp; vnconſtant, changeable in their Affections, and ſoone diſtaſte what they did earneſtly deſire. Their Paſſions are violent for the time, but they doe quickly vaniſh: their Wills are like the hunger and thirſt of ſickly perſons, wonderfull ſharp, but of no long continuance. They are exceeding prone to anger, impatient of iniuries, vnapt to ſwallow baſe indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and alwayes more ambitious then couetous. They care not for looking after profit, becauſe they neuer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of bitter want. Mallce and ſubtile craft are like ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, altogether vnacquainted with their boſomes: they haue not yet proceeded in the ſchoole of worldly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and are therefore ignorant, plaine, and ſimple.</p>
               <p>They are eaſie of beliefe, and credulous, as hauing not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19386:26"/> beene often entangled with the ſophiſticall proceedings of baſe deceit. The greateſt prop whereon they reſt their life, is Hope of future accidents: which notwithſtanding it emboldeneth their mindes, and maketh them conſtant, layeth them open, and vnfenced, to treacherous and ſlye inuaſion. They are ſhamefaſte, modeſt, and withall mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous. In matters of action they alwayes prefer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie before gaine. It is Vertue that guideth them, and not Diſcourſe; which argueth profit to be the onely aime and ſcope of the intention.</p>
               <p>They delight in mirth and laughter, and are by reaſon thereof exceeding ſtudious of acquaintance, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally making of appointments for publike meetings. As their actions are boundleſſe, ſo are their affections: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they hate or loue, or whatſoeuer they doe, they paſſe the bounds of meaſure and proportion. Their eyes are full of pittie, and their hearts are ſtored with compaſſion, at the ſight, or hearing of an other mans misfortunes, and diſaſters; becauſe that meaſuring him by their owne ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, they thinke him altogether vnworthie of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</p>
               <p>Old men are in a manner of a cleane contrary inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For hauing by reaſon of their yeares, and long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, diſcouered, that whatſoeuer is vnder the Sunne is vanitie, and liable to chaunce, they will not vtter their opinion poſitiuely in any thing, but vnder-value euery thing more then is requiſite or conuenient. Their diſcourſe is alwayes limited with doubts, and ſuppoſitions, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlaced with <hi>Peraduentures, It may bees,</hi> or other ſuch like tearmes of <hi>Moderation;</hi> ſo whatſoeuer they propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, they adhere to nothing. They are for the moſt part left-hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (that is to ſay) malicious, and apt to conſter all things to the worſt ſenſe. Their hardnes of beliefe doth furniſh them with matter of ſuſpition; and the knowledge they haue of worldly policie, doth authorize their incredulity. Their deſires are lightly of a lowe-built-roofe, and looke
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19386:26"/> but onely after thoſe things that may ſerue for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their life and being. Hence it is, becauſe riches are of the ſame ranke and liuery, as likewiſe, becauſe they are not ignorant that the waſting of wealth and ſubſtance is eaſie, but the purchaſe of it hard and difficult, they are in their expence ſo niggardly &amp; ſparing, that <hi>Plantus</hi> quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it as a wonder to ſee an old man bountifull, <hi>Benigni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as huius ſicut adoleſcentuli eſt.</hi> They are ſeldome valiant, but cowardly and full of feare: which as Philoſopers affirme, is occaſioned by the coldnes of their temper. For feare is nothing elſe but a frigiditie, or (as I may ſay) priuation of that vigorous heate, which doth enflame the bloods of younger men, and makes them careleſſe both of death and danger. They delight in accuſations and contentions, which is likewiſe a branche of <hi>Puſillanimitie;</hi> and where there is hope of gaine, they make no ſcruple to diſpence with honeſtie, not caring for the breath of rumour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte. Their owne timiditie, together with a long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued obſeruation of the mutability of worldly buſineſſes, and their frequent interruptions and miſcarriages, doth make them weake and feeble in their hopes and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. They be wondrous talkatiue, and loue to heare the ſtories of Antiquity, eſpecially ſuch as haue hapned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reuolution of their owne time, and wherein them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue peraduenture beene as Miniſters and Agents. They are apt enough to ſympathize with others in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of griefe, and tenderly to bemone the wretchednes of their condition: but this their Commiſeration is not the ſame with that of younger men. For the ground of it in theſe is courteſie and humanity, but in thoſe weakeneſſe and imbecility. They ſee their owne eſtate enuironed on euery ſide with dangers and inconueniences, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pittie others, becauſe themſelues are likely to endure the like. They are ſomewhat froward, querelous, and peeuiſh, apt to take exceptions at any thing; and withall, to checke &amp; contradict all courſes, but ſuch as their owne
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19386:27"/> experience hath eſtabliſhed, as Principles and infallible Maximes.</p>
               <p>Now thoſe of middle age, are as the meane betweene theſe two extreames, and doe alike participate of both. They are neither ouer-bolde, nor ouer-fearfull; but holde indifferently with either. They are not incredulous of all things, but ſhape their iudgement according to the rule of truth. They are not ſparing, nor yet prodigall, but cut their garment according to their cloth, and at all times accommodate their disburſements, and layings out, to the quantitie and proportion of their yearely commings in. Their modeſtie is backt continually with valour, and their valour neuer but ſeconded with modeſty: both which in youth and age are vtterly diſioyned. For young men are valiant, but immodeſt; old men are modeſt, but exceeding timorous. And to conclude all in one word, looke what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is commendable in either of the other two, being conſidered apart and by themſelues, is ſeeldome wanting in this: but whatſoeuer ſauoureth either of exceſſe, or of deficiencie in them, is but fit and moderate in theſe. The Poet, as appeareth by the verſes following, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced theſe differences into a briefer forme.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Imberbis iuuenis tandem cuſtode remoto,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Horat: Art: Poet.</note>
                        <hi>Gaudet equis, canibus<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, &amp; aprici gramine campi,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cereus in vitium flecti, monitoribus asper,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vtilium tardus proviſor, prodigus aeris,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sublimis, cupidus<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, &amp; amata relinquere pernix.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conuerſis ſtudijs aetas, animus<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> virilis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quaerit opes &amp; amicitias, inſeruit honori:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Commiſiſſe cauet, quòd mox mutare laboret.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Multa ſenem circumveniunt incommoda, vel quid</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quaerit, &amp; inuentis miſer abſtinet, ac timet vti:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vel quòd res omnes timidè, gelidè<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> miniſtrat,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dilator, ſpe longus, iners, auidus<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> futuri:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Difficilis, querulus, laudator temporis acti</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Se puero, cenſor, caſtigator<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> minorum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19386:27"/>
                     <l>The beardleſſe youth doth, freed from Tutors quite,</l>
                     <l>In horſe, in hounds, in champion fields delite;</l>
                     <l>To vice, like waxe, with eaſe he may be bent,</l>
                     <l>Hee harſhly brookes a Monitors intent;</l>
                     <l>In looking to his profite hee is ſlowe,</l>
                     <l>Nor cares he how his money he beſtowe:</l>
                     <l>Haughty he is, and full of hot deſire,</l>
                     <l>Ready to leaue, what loue did erſt require.</l>
                     <l>By ſtudies oppoſite the manly minde</l>
                     <l>Doth labour hard, both wealth and friends to finde,</l>
                     <l>He ſerues for honour, and doth take great heede</l>
                     <l>Of doing ought, which hee to change had neede.</l>
                     <l>The olde man ſeekes, yet like a wretch abſtaines,</l>
                     <l>And dares not taſte the ſweetnes of his paines;</l>
                     <l>He gouernes all things coldly, and with feare,</l>
                     <l>And in performance ſluggiſh doth appeare;</l>
                     <l>Puts buſines off, with doubts and ſtrange delayes,</l>
                     <l>And on his hopes makes long and tedious ſtayes.</l>
                     <l>To know things future greedily he longs,</l>
                     <l>Froward, peruerſe, complaining ſtill of wrongs;</l>
                     <l>Commends the times which hee a childe did viewe,</l>
                     <l>And will be <hi>Cenſurer</hi> of the younger Crewe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Now this which hath hitherto beene ſpoken, may ſerue as a light, whereby to diſcouer the reſt of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent properties and impreſſions, which by reaſon of theſe differences and mixtures, are daily ſtamped in the minde of man; as likewiſe by the temperature of the ayre, in which they liue, and the nature of the heauen, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they breathe; from whence <hi>S. Paul</hi> did reaſon and conclude, that thoſe of <hi>Crete</hi> were with ſharpnes and ſeuerity of diſcipline to be reprooued: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. The <hi>Cretanes</hi> are alwaies Lyars, euill beaſts, ſlowe bellyes;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit:</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 12.13.</note> and therefore (ſaith he) <hi>Rebuke them ſharply.</hi> So that now I
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19386:28"/> will paſſe from theſe, and ſpeake of ſuch as are externe, and bred but by the acceſſe of ſome vnlookt-for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
               <p>Such is the compoſition of mens internall affections, that the nobler they grow, the more ambitious they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. For there is none but deſireth alwayes to adde ſomewhat to his firſt acquiſt, and to enlarge the heape by new ſupplyes, and freſh accumulations. <hi>Plus vitrà</hi> is the ſoule of all their Emblemes and deuiſes. They loue not any ſhould be prayſed or commended but themſelues, and are apt withall to traduce the worth and good deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ſuch as are like their Anceſtors. For thoſe things which haue beene wrought and effected long agone, are farre more honourable, and affoord more matter for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation, then thoſe which were of late atchieued; ſo that the relation of them, ſhould it paſſe without ſome contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or embaſement of their price, might peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they thinke obſcure and dimme the luſtre of their owne.</p>
               <p>Such manners, cuſtomes, and inclinations as attend on riches may eaſily be diſcerned. They that are owners of neuer ſo little quantitie, are for the moſt part proud, and contumelious; They ſtand as highly conceited of themſelues, as if they had in their poſſeſſion where with to purchaſe the fee-ſimple of the whole world. For riches are indeede the price of whatſoeuer elſe is exiſtent in this earthly Globe, and by them alone the dignitie thereof is valued and eſteemed. They are daintie, and doe arrogate much vnto themſelues: the firſt, to expreſſe by way of boaſting thoſe pleaſures, and that happineſſe which they enioy; this other, becauſe that all men doe hunt and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after that which they themſelues adore with loue and admiration. They are ſeldome greatly troubled with iniuries or indignities, becauſe the number of thoſe that ſtand in neede of their helpe is in euery Towne and Citie very great. They challenge to themſelues precedencie of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19386:28"/> moſt men, and thinke that by reaſon of their great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance they ſhould be lords and rulers ouer all, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede they are. For as the Oracle of heauenly wiſedome hath aſſured vs, <hi>The rich ruleth the poore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 22. <hi>verſe</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>and the borrower is no better then a ſeruant to him that lendeth.</hi> But heere wee muſt obſerue, that the manners and behauiour of ſuch as haue attained to ſome eminent promotion but of late and on the ſuddaine, and theirs that haue enioyed their glory, and their large poſſeſſions a longer ſeaſon, are very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one from the other. All euils are more, and in a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degree of euill in them, then in the latter. For this ſame ſuddaine flowe and encreaſe of fortune doth ſo ſeldome better the diſpoſition, that as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reporteth,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vespaſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſolus omnium ante ſe principum in melius mutatus eſt.</hi> So much proſperitie doth oftentimes corrupt the wiſeſt, and vtterly ouerthrow the beſt compoſed natures, ſo that with <hi>Pindarus</hi> his <hi>Tantale,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not digeſt too great a happineſſe: wherevpon it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that their minds are ouercharged, and oppreſſed with crudities, and many vlcerous inflammations. That ſpuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and adulterate brat of rule, and ſoueraignetie, Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe, did ſo alter the noble conſtitution of <hi>Darius</hi> his princely minde, that he remaines a precedent to all poſteritie; <hi>homines cum ſe permisêre fortunae, etiam na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uram dediſcere.</hi> Of himſelfe he was milde, and tractable: but the condition of his State corrupted many times the ſtate of his condition, and puffed him vp with ſuch conceites as were afterwards vpon more ſetled conſideration vtterly diſallowed. <hi>Curt. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, there is a difference in manners, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth onely from a difference in nouriture and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this was well expreſſed by <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> when in the preſence of all the <hi>Lac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>daemonians</hi> he brought forth two Grey-hounds, both of one breeding, though not of one bringing vp, and ſet before them a pot of Pottage, and a Hare; which was no ſooner on foote, but that which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19386:29"/> had beene formerly accuſtomed to the field, did ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vndertake it, and forgot the gruell to purſue the game; whereas the other that had beene alwayes a Tenant to the Kitchin, as nothing moou'd with that inticement, fell cloſely to his lap. All men are eyther ignorant, and ruſticall, or ingenuous and liberall; the firſt are, as the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian calleth them, <hi>humanate bestie,</hi> ſuch, as by reaſon of that ſmall proportion of vnderſtanding which is in them, care not but to ſatisfie their ſenſuall appetites, and are wonne to nothing which is not either profitable or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant.</p>
               <p>Since all men therefore doe approue that ſpeech which hath the neereſt affinitie and reſemblance with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and which is fitteſt accommodated to the priuate motions and propenſions of their owne humours and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, I ſhall not neede to furniſh him with any other precept, or inſtruction, but onely this, That he varie his Rhetoricall proofes, inductions and perſwaſions, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature and diſpoſition of his Auditors; <hi>vt quaelibet eorum diuerſa genera per plures dicendi ſpecies teneat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plin. Sec. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> For one and the ſame thing, if intended to ſeuerall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, muſt be vttered to them all reſpectiuely, and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wayes; and therefore let him be as the Poet ſayth,
<q>Orpheus in ſyluis, inter Delphinas Arion.</q> For without this voluble and winding application, he may well write or ſpeake, but he ſhall neuer be able to preuaile.</p>
               <p>To negotiate with men by letters, vnleſſe in caſes wherein he would aduantage himſelfe by the reply, is dangerous, vncertaine, and inconuenient. Firſt, becauſe in them he layeth himſelfe more open to their Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then in ordinarie Conference, in which his words are altogether Curſorie, and cannot poſſibly be marked, or conſidered, but by glimpſes, and in paſſage. Secondly, becauſe they doe oftentimes miſcarrie, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19386:29"/> by reaſon of that, may many wayes prooue hurtfull and preiudiciall. Laſtly, becauſe they are ſubiect to diſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, wreſtings, deprauations, and inconſtructions.<note place="margin">Plin. Sec. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem vultus, geſtus, vox ipſa moderatur: Epiſtola omnibus commendationibus deſtituta malignitati interpretantium expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is better to deale with men by Attornie, then in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: for ſo ſhall he drawe all things on the ſuddaine and without premeditation from them; but himſelfe get time to deliberate and thinke vpon the buſineſſe, and returne their words that anſwere, which is moſt conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for his owne turne: beſides, if the partie that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed be wiſe, and well experienced in matters of the world, many articles and couenants may be vnder-hand agreed vpon, which himſelfe if after-occaſions ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the performance of them to be cumberſome, may diſavow, as hauing paſt without his knowledge and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; and ſo finde meanes to free himſelfe from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, by making his ſtartings and departures to his owne advantage. But theſe Revocatorie procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in matters wherevnto his iudgement, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of a third, hath formerly conſented, are but ſophiſticall and deceitfull Elenches; yea, ſuch as cannot be practiſed without diſhoneſtie and ſoyle of reputation. And now will I paſſe from this, to come to that, which is more particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19386:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. Of the ſeuerall kindes of Negotiation, viz: the Iudiciall, Deliberatiue, and Demonſtratiue: <hi>their ſeuerall vſes, natures and proprieties.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſoeuer is the ſubiect or occaſion of Entercourſe, and Debatement, is either Iudiciall, Deliberatiue or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratiue. The firſt conſiſteth in accuſing, and defending, in demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and denying; and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnder it all ſuch ſpeeches as are either <hi>Conquestorie, Expoſtulatorie,</hi> or <hi>Refutatorie:</hi> The ſecond in exhorting and dehorting, and compriſeth ſuch as are <hi>Gratulatorie, Complementall,</hi> or <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious:</hi> The third and laſt is altogether exerciſed in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and diſprayſing, and containeth in it ſuch as are <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, Commenda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orie, Deprecatorie, Conſolatorie, Obiurgatorie,</hi> and the like. So that nothing is at any time in queſtion or controuerſie betweene man and man, but it may well be referred to ſome one of theſe. And therefore hauing once diſcouered to what kinde of cauſe, the matter which he is to treate of, be it by letter, by perſonall conference, or howſoeuer, doth naturally belong, he may ſtraightway know to what Topikes, heads, and common-places he ſhould repaire for arguments, examples and inductions, with other ſuch preparatorie ſtore, wherewith to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and corroborate his plea. <hi>Roſcius non occidit patrem,</hi> is a queſtion <hi>Coniecturall Iudiciall,</hi> and is therefore handled in places proper thereunto, viz. <hi>Voluntate &amp; Facultate:</hi> that <hi>Roſcius</hi> had neither the will to doe it, nor the meanes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the finall ayme, and ſcope of all his ſpeech will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by eaſily appeare. For not to ſtand vpon the generall
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19386:30"/> ends thereof, which are either <hi>Gnoſticall,</hi> and haue in them a plaine and open exhortation, either to Action or Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as appeareth in the <hi>Demonſtratiue,</hi> from whence we ſlide to the <hi>Deliberatiue;</hi> or <hi>Practicall,</hi> when any thing is expreſly commaunded, as hapneth oft in this and the <hi>Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall;</hi> I will onely handle thoſe that are more ſpeciall, as namely the perſon of the Orator, the perſon of the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and the qualitie of the thing: For in euery ſeuerall kinde, theſe three muſt with ſingular diſcretion and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement, be well conſidered.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Iudiciall</hi> it is the dutie of an Orator to act the Plaintife, or Defendant; the part of a Iudge to put on the habit of Mildnes, or Seueritie; and the propertie of the Thing to be iuſt, or vniuſt; lawfull, or vnlawfull.</p>
               <p>In the Deliberatiue the Speaker muſt altogether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade or diſſwade; the hearer, either hope, or feare; and the thing it ſelfe make ſhew of profit, or of detriment.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Demonſtratiue,</hi> the firſt muſt praiſe or diſpraiſe; the ſecond be ſomewhat delighted with what is ſpoken; and the laſt ſeeme good and honeſt, or of a contrarie graine. And thus much of their ends. Now will I delineate and deſcribe in a more exact and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fect manner the ſtate of euery ſeuerall kinde, and firſt of that which is <hi>Iuridicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is entituled by Rhetoricians <hi>Status qualitatis,</hi> a State of qualitie, becauſe in it the nature of the fact is examined, ſifted, and defyned, whether it partake with Equitie, or Vniuſtice; as likewiſe becauſe in it the queſtion for the moſt part is <hi>de iure:</hi> And it is twofolde, <hi>viz.</hi> of the time paſt, and a thing alreadie done, which indeed is properly that State, which we ſurname <hi>Iuridicall;</hi> or of the time to come, and whether a thing may iuſtly be done, or no; which kinde of Conſtitution we call <hi>Negoti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll.</hi> The <hi>Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtate</hi> is likewiſe twofolde; <hi>Abſolute,</hi> when without aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming any thing for the confirming, or approuing of what is done, we pronounce by ſome direct Enunciation, it is rightly done: or <hi>Aſſumptiue,</hi> when we lay hold on ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19386:31"/> ignorant and vnlearned are oftentimes more moued with contumelies and diſgraces, then with whatſoeuer is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt or vpright.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Compariſons,</hi> in regarde that ſomething may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, eaſie, profitable, and commodious in a higher degree then others; yea, they may ſeeme full often to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as where in <hi>Sophocles, Iſmene</hi> and <hi>Antigone,</hi> conſulting about the buriall of their brother; the one reſpected one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honeſty, the other, nothing but ſecurity, and the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, <hi>Affects</hi> and <hi>Motions,</hi> but eſpecially in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſome moment and importance. <hi>Your Anceſtors,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tullie,</hi>) in his oration for <hi>Manilius, haue often waged warres to reuenge thoſe iniuries and indignities, which haue bene offered to their Merchants &amp; their Mariners. How then ought you to be affected after the bloudië maſſacre of ſo many thouſand Romane Citizens, &amp;c:</hi> where all the foure doe manifeſtly concurre, <hi>(viz:)</hi> the <hi>Example,</hi> the <hi>Compariſon,</hi> the <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> and the <hi>Motion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. Of the Demonſtratiue, where are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhowne the ſeuerall kindes thereof, together with the meanes how to <hi>enforce and preſſe them for aduantage. x. x.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Demonſtratiue</hi> is ſo entituled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in it the vertues and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a man are plainely ſhowne. Or becauſe in this kinde Rhetoricians doe moſt of all lay open &amp; vnfold the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ornaments and flowers of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence: by reaſon whereof, it may bewell ſuſpected to be ſomewhat the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19386:31"/> more ſophyſticall. <hi>Cicero</hi> calleth it <hi>exornati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nem,</hi> a kinde of beautifying; and <hi>Plato</hi> will haue it nothing elſe,<note place="margin">In Sophiſta.</note> then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſpeake with preparation, maieſtie, and pompe. The vſe of it is altogether <hi>Ethicall,</hi> and is apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but to reforme the minde. The matter of it is the ſame with that of the other two, from which it differeth onely in the handling. For the former conſiſt in precepts; this in expoſition. <hi>Glorie not in ſumptuous rayments, but let thy whole delight bee in the lawe of the Lorde,</hi> is a ſentence, which containeth in it inſtruction, counſaile, and direction; whereas, in ſaying by way of inſtance, That he gloried not in ſumptuous rayments, but his whole delight was in the law of the Lorde; we doe (but as it were) encomiaſtically expound the ſenſe and meaning of the firſt. Whoſoeuer therefore would commend, let him ſee what he would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; if command, let him ſee what he would commend, as a thing in manners decent and conuenient.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Demonſtratiue</hi> kinde of ſpeeche is either ſerious, as in the praiſing of <hi>Enagoras,</hi> in <hi>Iſocrates;</hi> or ſportfull, and for merriment, as that of the <hi>Flie</hi> in <hi>Lucian.</hi> The ſubiect thereof is threefold. For all praiſes are either of perſons, of deedes and atchiuements, or laſt of all, of things cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall and incorporeall. The handling of the firſt is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Naturall,</hi> or <hi>Artificiall. Naturall,</hi> when following the courſe of time, we make a direct enumeration and recitall of all ſuch worthy accidents, and remarkable points and paſſages, as may haue happened from the day of a mans birth, to the houre of his buriall. <hi>Artificiall,</hi> when wee mingle and confound them; or when by logicall diuiſions and diſtributions we referre them to certaine heads; as to the goods of the minde, of the bodie, or of Fortune; or thirdly, when we climbe vp from the leſſer to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or ſlide downe from the greater to the leſſer: or laſt of all, when ſmall things are enterueined with great; things darke and obſcure, with ſuch as are cleare, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and apparant; thoſe which are altogither incredible,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19386:32"/> with ſuch as are ſomewhat probable. Examples we haue of euery kinde; of the perſons in <hi>Demoſthenes, Iſocra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, Theoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tus,</hi> and diuers others, who by Epitaphes, by Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrikes, and ſuch like Epideicticall diſcourſes, haue publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vnto the world the good deſeruings of ſundry men: Of the deedes, in that Thankes-giuing of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to God for their deliuerance, <hi>Exod:</hi> 15. as likewiſe in many places of profane Authors. Of things themſelues, in <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie's</hi> booke <hi>De Senecture,</hi> where Pleaſure is vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and Husbandry abundantly commended; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, in the 11. of the <hi>Hebrues,</hi> where the bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> hauing defined the nature and the property of <hi>Faith.</hi> propounds vnto them an Encomiaſticall deſcription of the vertue, power, and efficacie thereof; and ſo in ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places.</p>
               <p>But for the auoyding of all ſuch inconueniences, as may happen in the handling of this kinde, wee muſt firſt of all obſerue an omiſſion, or at leaſt a ſpeedy expedition, and diſpatch of whatſoeuer may proue diſtaſtefull and vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoury in the vtterance; or ſecondly, wee muſt colour and diſguiſe it with ſome faire pretence: which like Ceruſe, or ſome other more artificiall beauty, may ſerue to ſhadowe whatſoeuer is eyther wrinkled or deformed: as where <hi>Iſocrates</hi> in his <hi>Helenes Encomio</hi> relateth, that ſhee was not ſtolne by <hi>Paris</hi> from her husband, for any luſt or wanton pleaſure, but by the prouocation of an ambitious deſire, which he had to be made and called the kinſ-man of <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> On the contrary, hee that diſpraiſeth any thing, will willingly make vſe of nothing but of defamatory traduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and reproches: and howſoeuer, now and then hee make ſome recapitulation of ſuch vertues and abilities, as are ſo manifeſt and apparant to the world, that he cannot, as he would, without ſome preiudice conceale them; yet notwithſtanding hee will be ſure neuer to propound them but with ſome daſh, that ſhall obſcure and blemiſh them, as in this, <hi>Caeſar fuit fortiſſimus, pationtiſſimus, Clementiſſimus:</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19386:32"/> where, in a moſt ingenuous and friendly manner, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſeemeth to acknowledge and confeſſe thoſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary parts and vertues, which were ſo eminent in <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> that the ſmothering of them would peraduenture haue argued and convinced him to be both enuious and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious: but that ſame, <hi>Haec omnia regni cauſâ,</hi> commeth in the rereward, and darkeneth all. But I cannot indeed approue of this. For it is but an adulterate kinde of skill, yea ſuch as is altogether diſauowed by <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Ariſtotle</hi> hath condemned ſuch as are fauourers of it, as hauing no other end, then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to deſtroy that which is good, by mingling it with what is bad.</hi> And indeed what is it elſe, then with that enuious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in the Goſpell, <hi>ſuperſeminare zizaniam &amp; abire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 25.</note> to ſowe tares ouer the wheate and then be gone? I vrge it not therefore as a precept,
<q>
                     <l>Ego ille ſum, qui ſcelera committi vetem:<note place="margin">Author Theb.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ego ſum magiſter iuris, &amp; moris probi.</l>
                  </q> I onely propound it as a meanes of Diſcouery.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, wee muſt firſt knowe, concerning this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtratiue</hi> kinde of ſpeeche, that in a drie and barren ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, <hi>plura tractantur acceſſoria, quàm rei propria;</hi> a man may drawe in many things, which are not altogether proper, or peculiar; and by way of digreſſion diſcourſe of ſundry matters, which carry but a ſide reſpect vnto the thing in hand. And hence it was, that <hi>Gorgias</hi> peraduenture did boaſte, he neuer wanted whereof to ſpeake. For if <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> (for example ſake) were at any time to bee commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the praiſes of <hi>Peleus, Aeacus,</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> would like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe follow.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That <hi>Opinion, Conceite,</hi> or <hi>Commendation,</hi> may ſupplie the roome and place of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> and <hi>Perſwaſion:</hi> as when we praiſe a Childe, or any other, for doing that, which we deſire to haue them doe; as likewiſe in that of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19386:33"/> 
                  <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Olynth.</hi> 1.</note> who ſpeaking to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> in ſtead of telling them, that it was their dutie to conſider what was needefull and conuenient for the Common-wealth, and not ſo gripingly retaine the money, which was to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſt for publike vſes; <hi>I beleeue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Athenians, that you more eſteeme the glorie of your Countrie, then any wealth, or treaſure whatſoeuer:</hi> which is a figuratiue and cunning kind of aggreſſion, and ſuch as may lawfully be practiſed, and with good ſucceſſe. It is eaſie for euery man liuing to erre, but ſo hard to wreſt from any mans mouth a plaine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of error, thar what hath once beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly reſolued vpon, the ſame is commonly perſiſted in, as long as wit, by whetting it ſelfe, is able to finde out any ſhift, be it neuer ſo ſlight, whereby to eſcape the hands of preſent Contradiction.<note place="margin">Deprehenſus pudor amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur. Sen.</note> But when wee ſee our faults paſſe vndiſcouered, and that we are prayſed for the contrary, we doe willingly, and of our owne accord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce our ſelues.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that in all things there be kept a true <hi>decorum,</hi> and a comelineſſe, and that hauing regard vnto the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, nothing be vttered, but what is honourable and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. And thus far of this. I will now come vnto thoſe parts of ſpeech, which are neceſſarily required for the better handling and enforcing of each ſeuerall kinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:19386:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. Of the ſeuerall partes, whereof all ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches doe conſiſt, whether they be Iudiciall, Deliberatiue, or Demonſtratiue, and <hi>of diuers points which are eſſentiall to the well compoſing of each.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeuerall parts whereof all ſpeeches, whether <hi>Iudiciall, Deliberatiue,</hi> or <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratiue</hi> doe vſually conſiſt, are ſixe, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Exordium,</hi> the <hi>Narration,</hi> the <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> the <hi>Confirmation,</hi> the <hi>Refutation,</hi> the <hi>Peroration,</hi> or <hi>Concluſion.</hi> The <hi>Exordium</hi> is properly that part, by which the minde of whoſoeuer is the Auditor, is made fit &amp; willing to embrace the ſequele. <hi>Tullie</hi> calleth it <hi>veſtibulum &amp; aditum ad cauſam,</hi> an entrance or portall into the cauſe. And it is direct and manifeſt, as when by open and perſpicuous motiues we doe incite the hearer to attention; or it is winding and oblique, as when by bouts and circuits we labour couertly to ſurprize him. The Greekes haue termed this an Incantation, the Latines an Inſinuation. It was practiſed with no meane ſucceſſe by <hi>Sinon,</hi> when being brought before king <hi>Priamus,</hi> he did endeauour by a true confeſſion of ſome things in the beginning, to make the better paſſage for thoſe treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous lyes, which he intended ſhould follow after.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Cuncta equidem tibi Rex,<note place="margin">Vir. Aeneid. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> fuerint quaecunque fatebor</l>
                  <l>Vera; <hi>ſaith he,</hi> neque me Argolica de gente negabo.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And it is the ordinary practiſe of Deceit,<note place="margin">Liv. lib. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>fidem in paruis ſibi praeſtruere, vt cum operaepretium ſit, cum mercede magna fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat,</hi> ſaith our Hiſtorian.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:19386:34"/>
               <p>It is needefull when the matter in hand is ſuch, as either for the groſeneſſe or the ſtrangeneſſe thereof, may alienate the mindes and affections of the hearers from vs; or when they are before-hand otherwiſe perſwaded; or laſt of all, when wee perceiue that they doe faint, and are growne weary of hearing. <hi>Sentio Iudices,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cicero, occurrendum eſſe ſatietati aurium, animorumque veſtrorum. Quamobrem multa praetermittam. Ad ea autem quae dicturus ſum, reficite vos, quaeſo Iudices, per Deos immortales, dum id Verris facinus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoro, quo tota prouincia Sicilia commota eſt;</hi> and this euen towards the end of his ſixt Oration againſt <hi>Verres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The onely aime of an <hi>Exordium</hi> is chiefely to beget be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence, which if the cauſe be doubtfull, and ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, muſt of neceſſitie be procured, and that from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the things. The perſons eyther are our ſelues, and ſuch as we defend, and pleade for; or ſecondly, they are our hearers; or laſt of all our aduerſaries. It is drawne from our owne perſons by a modeſt commendation of our abilities and deſerts; as likewiſe by a commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and recitall of our cares and troubles; the firſt is <hi>Et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call;</hi> the other in a meane <hi>Patheticall;</hi> or by a refutation, and remouall of ſuch obſtacles and impediments as may any way be hurtfull and preiudiciall to vs. From the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our Auditors, by alleaging their prayſes; or by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them know the hope and eſtimation which men haue of them. <hi>Fide ſapientiaque veſtra fretus,</hi> ſaith the Orator, <hi>plus oneris ſuſtuli quàm ferre me poſſe inteſtigo.</hi> Laſt of all, from the perſon of our Aduerſaries, by bringing them into hatred through ſome particular relation of whatſoeuer villanies and enormities haue bin committed by them; or by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to enuy, by ſome cunning blazoning of their wealth, birth, power, and authoritie, as things on which they more rely, then on the vprightneſſe of their cauſe: or thirdly, by cauſing them to be contemned through ſome rehearſall of their ſlothfulneſſe, their ignorance, and other ſuch like weakeneſſes and imperfections.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:19386:34"/>
               <p>An other end to be conſidered in the well compoſing of an <hi>Exordium,</hi> is the begetting of attention; which is eaſily obtained, if we ſignifie vnto our Auditors, that we are to ſpeake of matters of importance; ſuch as neerely concerne the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, are neceſſarie to be knowne, and carrie with them profit and delight. <hi>Vtiliſſima munera,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſi non perinde popularia, comitate orationis inducenda.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this we muſt imitate the wiſe Phyſitians, <hi>qui ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, ſed voluptate carentes cibos blandioribus alloquijs proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur.</hi> Or laſt of all, if in lowe and humble manner we craue, and beg it at their hands.</p>
               <p>A third and laſt end is, to inſtruct the hearer in the cauſe, if ſo it be obſcure; and for his better information to epitomize and abridge the buſineſſe, letting him ſee the ſumme of it, firſt in ſome generall propoſition, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in ſome particular diuiſion.</p>
               <p>Now theſe in regard of the conceites and opinions which men haue oftentimes both of the perſons and the things, are with all diligence to be conſidered: to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that hauing vnderſtood how all men ſtand affected to our Cauſe, and knowing what they thinke both of the Plaintiffe, and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fendant; as likewiſe what either friends or enemies could wiſh were principally done, we may thereafter for our beſt aduantage, frame and compoſe the beginning of our ſpeech.</p>
               <p>There are ſome <hi>Proëms,</hi> which ſeeme, as it were, inartifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, and withall ſomewhat remooued from the Cauſe in hand, but are notwithſtanding very cunningly connexed with it, and they are either <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riſtaticall,</hi> ſuch as are drawne from circumſtances, as from Time, Place, and the like; or they be <hi>Gnomicall,</hi> ſuch as are taken from Sentences, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbes, Examples, Precedents, and Cuſtomes.</p>
               <p>Thoſe haue in them alwaies the beſt grace which are grounded vpon the ſpeeches of our aduerſe partie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that ſeeming not to haue bene indicted at home, but inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted there, the readineſſe of wit brings an encreaſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19386:35"/> of fame; and the ſhew of Simplicitie an acquiſt of faith. <hi>Quo minus cupiditatis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Liu. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Dec. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ac ſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ij v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a eſt oratio hubere, eo plus authoritatis habuit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Liuie,</hi> ſpeaking of that Oration, which <hi>Apollonides</hi> the <hi>Siracuſan</hi> applied to the diſtempered mindes of his diuided countrimen. <hi>Ea demum magna vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cicero) Crispe Salluſti, aequalem, ac parem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vitam agere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Retor: lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> From whence we muſt obſerue according to that principle of <hi>Ariſtotles,</hi> that he which is Plaintiffe muſt moſt of all enforce his accuſations in the Epilogue, but the Defendant muſt in the very firſt beginning refell all ſcandalous imputations, that may hurt, or hinder.</p>
               <p>Such as are puffed vp and ſwolne, are vtterly to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded; as likewiſe thoſe, which are vulgar, and may ſerue for many cauſes; or common, and which our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries may vſe as well as we, with diuers others as vitious and defectiue in ſome regard as theſe.</p>
               <p>Sometimes they may be altogether omitted, as in <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> which are onely narratorie: yet in matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they cannot be neglected, no not of the <hi>Athenians</hi> themſelues, who were compelled by the Law to ſpeake without <hi>Exordiums</hi> or <hi>Affects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the <hi>Exordium</hi> commeth the <hi>Narration,</hi> which is nothing elſe, but an expoſition of things done, or reputed to be done. Sometimes there is a kinde of preparation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed, that it may ſeeme to cohere the better with the former. For it is not fit we ſhould ſuddainely ruſh vpon any thing, but come vnto it ſeaſonably, and by degrees. Now euery Narration is <hi>Grammaticall,</hi> or <hi>Oratoriall.</hi> A <hi>Grammaticall Narration</hi> is that which is remooued from ciuill pleas, and yet is vſed for the better handling of ſuch as are <hi>Oratoriall:</hi> and it is of Perſons, and expreſſeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward manners, and the outward ſhape; or of Things, and is either <hi>Hiſtoricall,</hi> containing in it an act done; or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> and fained, whoſe argument is onely but a fiction, yet ſuch as may be done; or <hi>Mythicall</hi> &amp; fabulous, reporting that which neuer was done, nor is euer likely to be done.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:19386:35"/>
               <p>The <hi>Oratoriall narration</hi> is that which appertaineth to Ciuill cauſes, and is vſed, as may appeare in all the Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Demoſthemes</hi> and <hi>Cicero,</hi> as a ſpeciall meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ouerthrow our aduerſarie, and obtaine the victorie. It is either <hi>Generall,</hi> or <hi>Speciall:</hi> the firſt is the chiefe and primarie <hi>Narration</hi> of the whole cauſe, and as I may ſay, the ſeate and foundation, whereon we ground the faith and credit of our matter: the laſt is a <hi>Digreſſion,</hi> which hapneth ſometimes vpon ſome certaine reaſon mouing vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. The generall <hi>Oratoriall Narration</hi> is either <hi>Simple,</hi> as in this; <hi>Occiditur ad Balneas Palatinas redi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns à coe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a S. Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> where neither the manner of the murther is ſet downe, nor any other circumſtance, that might argue the truth of that aſſertion. And here we muſt note, that thoſe things, which depreſſe and ſad the ſpirits of our Auditors, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be vttered but with exceeding breuitie; whereas thoſe that are well reliſhed and accepted by them, are to be reſted on ſome longer time. And thus doth <hi>Homer</hi> make <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> to relate the ſtories of his wandring trauailes at large to thoſe of <hi>Corcyra.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Odyſſ: lib. <hi>9.</hi> vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad lib. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> who were themſelues men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, and ſtudious of reports: Or ſecondly, it is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and in it are ſowne the ſeedes of a future <hi>Confirmation:</hi> Or thirdly, it is magnificent, and deſcribeth all things ſo exactly, and in ſuch amplifying manner, that we ſeeme as it were to behold them with our eyes: Or laſt of all, it is delightfull, and is vſed more for pleaſure then neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>The elements whereof <hi>Narrations</hi> doe conſiſt, are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, which <hi>Plutarke</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">In vita Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meri.</note> 
                  <hi>the occaſions of euery expoſition;</hi> and they are either,
<list>
                     <item>1. Perſons.</item>
                     <item>2. Things done.</item>
                     <item>3. Things pretermitted in the doing.</item>
                     <item>4. Reaſons and inducements mouing men to either.</item>
                     <item>5. Opinions, Counſailes, Aduiſes and Conceits.</item>
                     <item>6. The place where.</item>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:19386:36"/>
                     <item>7. The time, when.</item>
                     <item>8. The manner, how: in which the preparation, together with ſuch inſtruments as did belong to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance are likewiſe ſhowne.</item>
                     <item>9. The finall iſſue and euent of all.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>After the <hi>Narration</hi> followeth the <hi>Propoſition,</hi> which is the State it ſelfe, or the principall Queſtion, to which all proofes and arguments are referred. The <hi>Narration</hi> may be ſometimes omitted, as in diſputations, ſuaſorie Cauſes, and iudgements, as likewiſe when the thing is manifeſt and knowne: but the <hi>Propoſition</hi> muſt be alwaies implyed at leaſt; for it is the ſcope of the contention: and to ſpeake, and not propound the ſumme of the matter, what is it elſe but to beate the ayre, and to encounter with a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe? It is the life or ſoule of Speech, and is proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly diffuſed through euery part and member of the ſame.</p>
               <p>It hapneth ſometimes, that in one and the ſame cauſe there may be many ſeparate <hi>Propoſitions;</hi> as when <hi>Socrates</hi> was accuſed in <hi>Xenophon</hi> to haue corrupted the younger ſort,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apomne:</hi> 1.</note> and to haue brought in ſuperſtitions that were neuer heard of. Sometimes againe there may be many, but all of them depending vpon ſome one more principall: ſo that heere it is neceſſarie and conuenient, there ſhould be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion and enumeration of all ſuch parts, as we would han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, together with ſome information of thoſe, which we were minded to omit. But heere we muſt beware that this diuiſion conſiſt not of more then three, or foure bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches at the moſt; and that, for feare the memorie through ouer many might happily be ſurcharged; or that exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this kinde ſhould be made an argument of dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Meditation: for which reſpect, <hi>Partitions</hi> many times are not at all to be obſerued. But being ſeaſonably applied, they grace and beautifie the ſpeech exceedingly; Beſides, the Auditors remember, and conceiue things with more facilitie, and are withall refreſhed, when they knowe how much they are to heare.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:19386:36"/>
               <p>The Confirmation is an expoſition of our arguments, accompanied with an aſſeueration, and is referred who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the prouing and authorizing of the State, or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall queſtion, which if that once faint, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie fall. In it the matter and forme, whereof our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments conſiſt, muſt of neceſſitie be both conſidered: and withall wee muſt obſerue, that if they be firme and ſound, they may be placed in it ſeuerally by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and with ſome diſtance one from an other: but if they be weake and crazie, they muſt be heaped vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that what they want in ſtrength, may be ſupplyed in number.</p>
               <p>The Confutation is nothing elſe but a diſſoluing of whatſoeuer our aduerſe partie ſhall alleage towards the weakening and impugning of our Cauſe,<note place="margin">Fab. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> which muſt be followed with exceeding diligence: becauſe as it is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to heale then to hurt, ſo is it to defend then to accuſe. <hi>Ad reprehendenda aliena facta aut dicta ardet omnibus animus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Salluſt. de Rep. ordin. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vix ſatis aperium os, aut lingua prompta videtur, quae meditata pectore euoluat.</hi> It is two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi> eyther of the Forme, as when we ſhew their Conſequences and Collections to be bad, or of the Matter, which for the diuerſitie of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is very diuers. For that which is doubtfull and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous can not be refelled, but by diſtinguiſhing; that which is falſe, no otherwiſe then by an abſolute deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, together with an allegation of ſuch reaſons as moue vs to denie it; yet ſometimes it may be ſeconded with a diuiſion, which is a larger and more copious kind of defence, the Negation being graunted <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> as Rhetoricians tearme it, as in this; <hi>Say that Roſcius had beene hated of his father, yet can it not be hence concluded, that hee would haue killed him; the accuſer therefore ſhould haue alleaged ſome weightier cauſe for his conuiction.</hi> Thoſe things which are light, and of little moment, muſt bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly ſet vpon, that ſo the troupe may be the better ſcattered.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:19386:37"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pophthegm.</note>
                  <hi>Scilurus</hi> lying on his death-bed, eaſily broke thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, that were then brought vnto him, one by one, which being bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d together, none of his foureſcore ſonnes were able to doe. And thus by the appointment of <hi>Serto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> a ſickly man did likewiſe without ſtrayning of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at all, plucke euery haire from out the taile of a ſtrong and luſty horſe;<note place="margin">Idem in vita Sertorij.</note> which an able and well diſpoſed Souldier taking holde of the whole taile of one feeble and ready to dye, with both his hands could neuer doe: Sometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, they are refuted by a deflexion from the thing, to a reprehenſion of the perſon. <hi>Cum hoc modo accuſas Eruci, nonne hoc palam dicis? Ego quid acceperim ſcio, quid dicam neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio. Vnum illud ſpectaui, quod Chryſogonus aiebat, neminem iſti patronum futurum;</hi> ſaith <hi>Cicero</hi> in his defence for <hi>Roſcius:</hi> where the three former are to the matter, but the fourth digreſſeth from the matter to the perſon.</p>
               <p>Common things are beſt refelled by <hi>Inverſion,</hi> when we ſhewe the ſignes or cauſes, which are brought againſt vs, to make directly for vs: as in this. <hi>Occidiſti, quia ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijſti;</hi> Thou ſlueſt him, becauſe thou buriedſt him. <hi>Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my burying of him, is an argument that I did not ſlay him. For had I ſlaine him, I would haue ſooner fled, then ſtayde to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie him.</hi> So that the parts of this inverting kinde of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation</hi> are two. For firſt, there is a <hi>Negation</hi> of the ſigne, and then a reaſon of this Negation. Or ſecondly, they may be ouerthrowne by <hi>Violation,</hi> which is a forcible retorting of our aduerſaries allegations on himſelfe, and differeth from <hi>Inverſion,</hi> in that it is <hi>Apologeticall,</hi> and defendeth; whereas the other is alſo <hi>Categoricall,</hi> and accuſeth. The one is like <hi>Marcellus</hi> with his ſword; the other like <hi>Fabius</hi> with his ſhielde. It is of greateſt power, in that it is leaſt looked for, and cannot (being well purſued) but procure the victory.<note place="margin">Heliodor. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> In a word, it is nothing elſe, then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to cut a mans throte, with his owne weapons.</hi> Or thirdly, by <hi>Abſolution,</hi> when wee interprete the ſignes or cauſes, otherwiſe then our aduerſary. Hee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19386:37"/> with ſcandall and maliciouſly; wee with ſome colour to the better part, as in this, <hi>Sepelij, &amp;c. I buried him, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſlue him, but becauſe I had compaſſion on him.</hi> Things impertinent, and not belonging to the queſtion, may be reiected and contemned, as not deſeruing any other refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Things cleare and manifeſt, may be confronted with ſome contrary <hi>Argumentation,</hi> or <hi>Compenſation;</hi> or by ouer-whelming the hearers memory with infinite <hi>Digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> which is indeede a ſpeciall kinde of ſupplanting, and ſuch as <hi>Aeſchynes</hi> deſired the Iudges to obſerue in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Peroration</hi> is the vtmoſt bounde of euery ſpeeche; or the <hi>Concluſion</hi> thereof, in which the principall <hi>Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is repeated. The parts of it are two, <hi>Enumeration,</hi> by which whatſoeuer was handled in a ſcattering, and diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed manner throughout the whole, is for remembrance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake reduced into one place; and is oftner to be vſed by the Plaintife, then by him that is Defendant. 2. <hi>Amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which is a more preſſing kinde of <hi>Affirmation,</hi> and ſuch as hauing mooued the mindes, begetteth credit, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. It is applyed, eyther to incenſe men againſt the wicked, or to mooue them to pittie the diſtreſſed.</p>
               <p>And thus farre of the ſeuerall parts, which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required in euery ſeuerall kinde of ſpeeche.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:19386:38"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. How to frame a Stile which may be correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent and agreeable to each ſeuerall kinde of <hi>Negotiation:</hi> Of the care which muſt be had in fitting it, both to the <hi>Perſon, and the Argument.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether it happen that a man be to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate in perſon, or by letter, he muſt be very carefull, that he deliuer and ſet downe his minde in ſuch a ſtile and phraſe, as may not be diſtaſtefull. For the effecting wherof, he muſt firſt haue a reſpect to the nature, ranke, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the perſons, with whome hee is to treate. For if they be ſuch as hauing in themſelues an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to doe well, carry not the leaſt peece of an eare, that can ſwallowe, much leſſe digeſt a vulgar conceite it will behooue him ſo to frame it, as that it may ſeeme of pompe, yet free from affectation.</p>
               <p>He muſt not make it ſauour ſo much of art, as of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Courtly magnificencie, which by a kinde of analogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call proportion, may ſomewhat anſwere the greatnes of the partie, to whom he either writes or ſpeakes. If it be to one of high place and publike action, he muſt endeuour to be briefe, but withall perſpicuous.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cùm tot ſuſtineas, cùm tanta negotia ſolus;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Hor: lib: <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt: <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>Res Italas armis tuteris; moribus ornes;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Legibus emendes; in publica commoda peccem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si longo ſermone morer tua tempora Caeſar.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such great affaires ſince thou alone ſuſtain'ſt;</l>
                     <l>And by thy armes th'Italian weale maintain'ſt;</l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19386:38"/>
                     <l>Since thou alone with manners it adorneſt,</l>
                     <l>And her defects by prudent Lawes reformeſt,</l>
                     <l>I ſhould (great <hi>Caeſar</hi>) wrong the publike good,</l>
                     <l>If with long ſpeeches I thy times withſtood:</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Saith <hi>Horace,</hi> writing to the <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now for the difference of mens natures, let him remember the complaint of the Poet,
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tres mihi conuivae propè diſſentire videntur,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Hor: lib: <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                           </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Poſcentes vario multùm diuerſa palato.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Three Gueſts I haue, which plainely diſagree,</l>
                        <l>Asking ſtrange things, with differing taſte, of mee:</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> And haue alwayes a diſh in ſtore for euery mans content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: So that whether,
<q>
                     <l>Carmine gaudebit; vel delectetur Iambis;</l>
                     <l>Siue Bionaeis ſermonibus, &amp; Sale nigro:</l>
                  </q> Hee may finde out a plate for his owne Palate. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he muſt haue regard in the compoſing of his ſtile to the quality and proprietie of the Subiects, whereof hee is to treate; varying it, as occaſion ſhall require, in a fit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent manner, according to the diuerſitie of the ſame. And looke what paſſions he would ſtirre vp in others, hee muſt firſt ſo expreſſe them in it, as he may ſeeme to be affected with the ſame himſelfe;
<q>
                     <l>—Triſtia moestum</l>
                     <l>Vultum verba decent; iratum, plena minarum;<note place="margin">Horat: de arte Poët.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ludentem laſciua; ſeuerum, ſeria dictu.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Hee that would moue compaſſion in my heart, muſt ſhew it in his owne. Griefe is the childe of Griefe, and Teares are ſeldome procreated but by Teares: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Poet ſaith,
<q>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:19386:39"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>— <hi>Malè ſi manda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>a loquetur,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aut dormitabo, aut ridebo:</hi> —</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If with bad vttrance he his part diſgrace,</l>
                        <l>Or ſleepe I will, or floute him to his face.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q> For where there is a want of this conueniency, what other effect can poſſibly be produced but laughter &amp; contempt?</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Romani tollent equites, pedites<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> cachinnum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The nobler Crue, and eke the baſer Croude,</l>
                     <l>Will burſt their Spleens, with laughing ouer-loude.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Hee muſt not ſtuffe it with words of a prodigious great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſuch as the Poet tearmes-<hi>ampullas, &amp; ſeſquipedalia ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba;</hi> and cannot by reaſon of their ouer-growne quantitie be vttered without ſome dangerous extenſion of the voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces inſtruments. <hi>Aeſchynes</hi> condemned them in <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Monſtroſa oratio mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroſae mentis indicium.</note> and branded them for euer with an opprobrious marke, calling them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>portenta, non verba:</hi> they muſt therefore of neceſſitie be auoyded. But now and then, he may eaſily, as occaſion requireth, diſpence with this. <hi>Plinie</hi> reported of a certaine Orator, becauſe of the continued lowneſſe of his ſtile, <hi>That he offended i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nothing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nihil peccat niſi quod ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil peccat. lib. <hi>9.</hi> Ep. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but in that he did not offend. Debet enim Orator,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>erigi, attolli, interdum etiam efferueſcere, efferri, ac ſaepè ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere ad praeceps.</hi> For an Orator muſt be erected, lifted vp; yea, ſometimes he muſt grow hote, beare himſelfe hye, and very often be readie to fall downe head-long. <hi>Tutius per plana, ſed humilius, &amp; depreſſius iter.</hi> It is onely for weake and crazie bodies to couet euen wayes: he that is ſtrong and able, will make no difficultie to try his legs, ſometimes euen in a rugged path, or if occaſion ſerue, to breathe himſelfe vp ſome hye and ſteepe aſcent. Such as doe run, are far more apt to fall, then thoſe that creepe;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19386:39"/> but theſe haue neuer any commendation, though they doe not fall: the others though they doe, haue alwayes ſome. <hi>Nam vt quaſdam artes, ita eloquentiam, nihil magis quàm ancipitia commendant.</hi> For it is with Eloquence as with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artes, nothing more beautifies and ſets it forth, then doubtfull and ambiguous accidents. Wee ſee what cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and what cryes reſound throughout the Theater, when thoſe that walke there vp the ropes, ſtand capring ſafely on the top, ſcorning the danger, which euery loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker on fully preſum'd they would haue falne into. Thoſe things are alwayes moſt admired, which are leaſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and cannot be performed but with exceeding ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard.</p>
               <p>He muſt not confound thoſe things which are of a ſoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and loftie ſtraine, with thoſe that are altogether full of winde and tumour; nor cenſure that as <hi>hyperbolicall,</hi> which well conſidered, is but round and full. Whatſoeuer ouerpeereth, and is eminent in any thing, may eaſily be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned: but we muſt weigh with iudgement and with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>immodicum ſit an grande; altum an enorme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He muſt with all dexteritie enterveine it with the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt ornaments that either words or ſentences can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly afford,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ne ſutorem quidem,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ageſilaüs, probum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, qui par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo pedi mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det calceum;</hi> when one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended a Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torician to him for his facultie, in making a great matter of a little. <hi>Plut.</hi>
                  </note> and beautifie it as far as the ſubiect whereof he treateth will beare, with <hi>Tropes</hi> and <hi>Metaphors,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch rhetoricall decencies. For he that would offer to draw <hi>Hercules</hi> his ſhooe vpon the foot of a child, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth no other recompence or hire, then laughter and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion for his paines. Let him herein therefore, like a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning workeman, faſhion his garments according to the making and proportion of him that is to weare them. Let not his ſpeech be either <hi>exiliter exanimata,</hi> or as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaith, <hi>gravius inſlata &amp; anhelata;</hi> but in all things as neere as may be correſpondent to his argument.</p>
               <q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hor. Art. Poët.</note>Nec dum vitat humum, nubes, &amp; inania captet.</q>
               <p>But there is notwithſtanding a certaine kinde of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification conſiſting both in words and ſentences, which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19386:40"/> may be vſed with commendation, when we would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll, aggrauate, or make worſe the matters that are in queſtion. The Greekes haue called it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe the tearmes, by which it is expreſt, do far ſurmount the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the thing. For they are either ſignificant, or weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and fill the minde: as when to make both Crime and Criminell the more deteſtable; in ſtead of the <hi>Genus,</hi> we alleage the <hi>Species;</hi> and whereas he did but hurt, affirme that he did kill: or ſecondly, they be forcible and violent of ſound, and fill the eares of thoſe that heare them; or thirdly they be full and round, and fill both their eares and mindes; or laſt of all, the better to make impreſſion, they be tropicall, and figuratiue: but theſe are neuer to be vſed, vnleſſe it be for neceſſitie ſake, when the proper word is wanting; or when, though it be extant, it is not altogether ſo expreſſiue and ſignificant; or for ornament ſake; or laſt of all for honeſtie, as when the proper word is ſuch as cannot be heard, or vttered, but with a bluſhing and baſhfull countenance; for all vnſauourines of ſpeech muſt vtterly be auoyded.<note place="margin">Saluſt: in Cicer:</note> 
                  <hi>Saepè grauius offendunt Auditorum animosij, qui aliena flagitia apertè dixerunt, quam ij, qui commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto belong all attributes and epithetes, which are nothing elſe but Adiectiues, borrowed eyther from the minde, or from the bodie, or extrinſecally from fortune, and fitly added to ſome Subſtantiue, to which they haue the like relation that ſawces haue to meates, and muſt therefore neuer be applyed but very ſparingly. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> condemn'd the writings of <hi>Alcidamas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rhetor: lib: <hi>3.</hi> cap: <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> as being <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, frozen, and ridiculous, by reaſon of his fond &amp; fooliſh affectation. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>For he vſeth not his Epithetes,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as ſawces, but as meates.</hi> True Eloquence is graue, and Matron-like in her behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; the apparell which ſhe weares is glorious, but not gawdie; it is comely, as well as coſtly: She loues not to be deckt with pide inuentions, like a Courtiſan; nor will
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19386:40"/> ſhe faſhion her ſelfe according to thoſe Indians, who not content to weare Eare-rings in ſuch place of the eares as is moſt naturall, and conuenient, thruſt Iewels through their noſe and lips, becauſe they will be ſure to be fine.</p>
               <p>To this ſame <hi>Auxeſis</hi> or <hi>Augmentation,</hi> is oppoſed <hi>Exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation,</hi> which is a leſſening, or diminiſhing of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is obiected, or propounded; as when in defenſorie pleas we make a Diminutiue of a Primitiue; or leauing the <hi>Species,</hi> haue recourſe to the <hi>Genus,</hi> and in ſtead of ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, name taking; in ſtead of wounding, touching. There is another kinde of <hi>Diminution,</hi> which in regarde it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from Modeſtie, is counted <hi>Ethicall,</hi> and is included in a Negatiue. The Souldier to free himſelfe from all ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of vaine-glory, which through an open profeſſion of his worth, he might haue eaſily incurred, gaue out, <hi>That hee was not vnexerciſed in deedes of armes, nor ill experienced in Martial diſcipline.</hi> And indeede the Negatiue is the ſame ſometimes with an Affirmatiue, as when for the auoyding of <hi>Tau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ologie,</hi> or the often repetition of one and the ſame word, wee ſay, <hi>Hee knoweth this, and is not ignorant of that:</hi> ſometimes againe, it importeth leſſe, as in this; <hi>Hospes quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nec malus, nec imprude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vir eſſe videris, &amp;c.</hi> where becauſe he was a ſtranger, &amp; vnknowne, it was thought ſufficient curteſie to beare a charitable opinion &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings, not attributing any vertue abſolutely vnto him, for feare his after-carriage might falſifie the report: and ſometimes more; as when <hi>Homer</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Achilles,</hi> when he beheld the meſſengers, which were come by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nons</hi> appointment to fetch his louely <hi>Briſis</hi> from him, in ſtead of ſaying, hee was wondrous ſad, relates, he was not very glad. But this may peraduenture ſeeme a little beſides the line, and be condemned as nothing pertinent or proper to the thing in hand, and therefore I will leaue it, and returne.</p>
               <p>As in the compoſition, ſo likewiſe in the ſelection and choyce of words, hee muſt not be too curious or preciſe;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19386:41"/> 
                  <hi>Cura verborum derogat affectibus fidem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quintil: lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; vbicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ars oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, veritas abeſſe videtur.</hi> Too great an affectation of them, argueth a light affection in the minde: and Truth is often thought to bee away, where Art is ſo predominant. Paſſions, if legitimate and vnfained, of what nature ſoeuer they be, can hardly faſhion themſelues to any Dialect, but their owne. Their ſpeeche is ſeldome of any long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nnance, but full of breakings and imperfect periods. The heart contendeth with the tongue for to expreſſe it ſelfe, but cannot finde the meanes: which <hi>Petrarke</hi> hauing diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in him ſelfe, ingenuouſly crieth out;
<q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Part:</hi> 1. <hi>Son:</hi> 138.</note>
                           <hi>I veggi' hor bien, che caritate acceſa,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lega la lingua altrui, gli ſpirti invola.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chi può dir com' egl'arde, e'n picciol fuoco.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now well I ſee, that true enkindled loue</l>
                        <l>The tongue doth binde, the ſpirites doth remoue.</l>
                        <l>Hee that hath wit, and words to tell his heat,</l>
                        <l>May feele ſome warmth, but ſure his flame's not great.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Let him therefore, the better to procure beliefe, make vſe of ſuch as may ſeeme like Voluntaries; of themſelues, and without preſſing, or conſtraint, to follow the leading of his Meditations, and marſhall them with ſuch dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that they may no way preiudice that feeling apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which he hath of what he is to treate.</p>
               <p>For the auoyding of prolixitie, then which nothing is more diſtaſtefull to a iudicious Auditorie, let him ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and contriue his ſpeech, digeſting the whole into ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry parts, and allotting to euery one their ſeuerall points, with ſuch conueniencie, <hi>vt ſaepe incipere, ſaepe deſinere videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> and that the <hi>Reader,</hi> if chance it were committed to writing, whereſoeuer hee ſhould beginne, whereſoeuer he ſhould ende, might finde it in all things ſo coherent, that reading where he left, he might thinke he began anew; ſo
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19386:41"/> that notwithſtanding hee ſeeme long and tedious in the vniuerſall,<note place="margin">Genus dice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ſecutus eſt Auguſtus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legas &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratum, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ineptijs, inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cinnitate, &amp; recondito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verborum, vt ipſe dicere ſolebat; foeto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus. Sueto: Sect: <hi>86, He did rebuke M. Antony for writing ſo that men might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wonder at him, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending in a certaine Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle the wit and apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion of</hi> Agrippina <hi>his Neece,</hi> Opus eſt da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re te operam, <hi>(ſaith hee)</hi> ne moleſtè ſcribas, aut loquaris: ib. in vita Aug:</note> hee may bee counted briefe in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <p>Let him not thinke to grace his ſtile, by cloathing it in the worme-eaten habit of decay'd <hi>Antiquitie;</hi> but alwayes vtter his Conceites in the beſt knowne, and moſt receiued phraſe, and in all things (as I ſaide before) labour to bee both plauſible and perſpicuous.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Hor: lib: <hi>2.</hi> Epi: <hi>2.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>Audebit quaecun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> parum ſplendoris habebunt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et ſine pondere erunt, &amp; honore indigna ferentur,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Verba mouere loco; quam vis inuita recedant:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Obſcurata diu populo bonus eruet, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Proferet in lucem ſpecioſa vocabula rerum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quae priſcis memorata Catonibus, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Cethegis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nunc ſitus informis premit, &amp; deſerta vetuſtas:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adſiſcet noua, quae genitor produxerit vſus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vehemens, &amp; liquidus, puro<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſimillimus amni,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t opes, patriam<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> beabit diuite lingua.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Luxuriantia compeſcet, nimis aspera ſano</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Laeuabit cultu; virtute caerentia tollet.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Slight words, and ſuch as little ſplendour haue,</l>
                     <l>Or by their worth, for honour cannot craue,</l>
                     <l>He ſhall with boldnes from their place remoue,</l>
                     <l>Though loth they ſeeme ſuch Cenſure to approue.</l>
                     <l>Vnto the people he (good man) ſhall ſhowe</l>
                     <l>Such as were long obſcur'd, as none did knowe;</l>
                     <l>And bring to light the ſpecious names of things,</l>
                     <l>Which practis'd were in time of ancient Kings:</l>
                     <l>Now buryed lye vnder th'oppreſſing rage</l>
                     <l>Of ill-ſhapt hoaryneſſe and forlorne age.</l>
                     <l>New ſhall he get, which <hi>Vſe</hi> hath made of worth,</l>
                     <l>And like a Riuer ſtreame his riches forth</l>
                     <l>In a ſwift courſe, but cleare and pure the while,</l>
                     <l>Gracing his Countrey with a wealthy ſtile.</l>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:19386:42"/>
                     <l>Such as doe riot, he ſhall curbe, reſtraine,</l>
                     <l>And make the rougher of a ſmoother graine;</l>
                     <l>But from his writings he ſhall baniſh quite,</l>
                     <l>Such as are bankroute of all force and might.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Laſt of all, let him adorne it with ſentences of ſundrie kindes;<note place="margin">De Orat: lib: <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> For without theſe, whatſoeuer can be ſaide, hath but a hollowe and an emptie ſounde: <hi>Nihil tam furio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tullie) quàm verborum vel optimorum, vel or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſſimorum ſonitus inanis, nulla ſubiecta ſententia, nec Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let him fitly therefore enterlace it with ſuch orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as learning can afforde; that by ſo doing, no <hi>Eupolis</hi> may Cenſure or condemne him to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Or, (as <hi>Salust</hi> ſaith) <hi>Loquacem magis quam facundum;</hi> a good talker, but a badde ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; or call him as <hi>Homer</hi> did <hi>Therſites,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a witleſſe and immoderate powrer forth of words.<note place="margin">Iliad: β</note>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſoule of <hi>Speech,</hi> and in theſe all the ſtrength and vigour of it doth conſiſt: for being beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with theſe, it ſeemes maieſticall and graue, and is enabled to make a deepe impreſſion in the hearts and mindes of ſuch as heare it; whereas without theſe it is altogether dull, and ſerues but as an Antike motion, to moue the laughter of the vulgar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:19386:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. Of Sentences tending to the beautifying of the Stile; their ſeuerall kindes, and <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations: with the Authors Apologie; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for a Concluſion to the whole.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
                  <hi>Sentence</hi> is a briefe but generall <hi>Enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation,</hi> concerning thoſe things, which belong to life and ciuill conuerſation. It eyeth not the <hi>Individuall,</hi> ſo much as the <hi>Vniuerſall;</hi> and cannot well be vſed, but where there is <hi>Election</hi> and choyce of action. It is firſt of all, either <hi>Simple; as</hi> this, <hi>Pleaſures the ſeldomer they be vſed, the more they are to be commended:</hi> or it is compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; as heere, <hi>Such is the nature and condition of an vnſteddie multitude, that it eſtimateth nothing according to truth, moſt things according to opinion.</hi> Secondly, it is poſitiuely true: as when we ſay, <hi>Religioſiſſimum eſſe Dei cultum, imitari;</hi> that <hi>Imitation</hi> is the moſt religious kinde of worſhip: or it is onely probable; as when we doe affirme, that <hi>Speech is the liuely Character of the Heart:</hi> and that <hi>Euery man reſembleth the Companie, which he keepeth:</hi> or it is <hi>Hyperbolicall,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it more then can be well beleeued by a vulgar apprehenſion: as, <hi>Omnes ſapientes ſunt liberi;</hi> There is no wiſe man but is free. Thirdly, it is <hi>hortatorie,</hi> or <hi>dehortatorie:</hi> as in the two laſt verſes of this <hi>Epigramme;</hi> which by reaſon of the elegancie thereof, I haue heere inſerted whole.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>uae faciunt beatiorem,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mart: lib. <hi>10.</hi> Epigr: <hi>47.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iucundiſſime Martialis, haec ſunt;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Res non parta labore, ſed relicta;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Non ingratus ager, focus perennis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:19386:43"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lis nunquam, toga rara, mens quieta,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vires ingenuae, ſalubre corpus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Prudens ſimplicitas pares amici,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conuictus facilis, ſine arte menſa;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nox non ebria, ſed ſoluta curis;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Non triſtis torus, attamen pudicus;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Somnus, qui faciat breues tenebras:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quod ſis eſſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lis, nihil<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> malis;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Summum nec metuas diem, nec optes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The things that make mans life more happie ſeeme,</l>
                     <l>Are theſe, delightfull <hi>Martiall,</hi> as I deeme:</l>
                     <l>Wealth not by labour got, but left by <hi>Will;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A fruitfull field, a fier burning ſtill;</l>
                     <l>Meane clothes, no ſtrife the mindes reſt to confound;</l>
                     <l>In different ſtrength, a body firme, and ſound;</l>
                     <l>Warie <hi>Simplicitie</hi> and equall friends;</l>
                     <l>An eaſie <hi>Diet,</hi> which no art commends;</l>
                     <l>The Night not drunke, yet looſe and free from care;</l>
                     <l>The bed not ſad, though chaſte beyond compare;</l>
                     <l>Sleepe, which may make the longeſt darkes but ſhort,</l>
                     <l>(Neuer diſturb'd with Thoughts of worldly ſort).</l>
                     <l>Be ſtill well-pleaſ'd, to be that which thou art,</l>
                     <l>And let thy choyce affect no greater part;</l>
                     <l>Feare not the day, which muſt thy life vp-ſumme,</l>
                     <l>Nor wiſh the ſame before the time doe come.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Liv: lib: <hi>5.</hi> Decad. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>Fourthly, it is <hi>Enunciatiue:</hi> as, <hi>In ſecundis rebus nihil in quenquam ſuperbè, ac violenter conſulere decet, nec praeſenti cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere fortunae, cùm quid vesper ferat incertus ſis.</hi> A man ſhould not ſaith <hi>Liuie</hi> in proſperitie determine any thing either violently, or proudly againſt an other, conſidering that he is vncertaine what the Euening may bring with it. Fiftly, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> teacheth vs, it is either <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> without a reaſon,<note place="margin">Rhetor: lib: cap: <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> being plaine enough of it ſelfe, and eaſie to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vnderſtood: as in this of <hi>Virgills,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:19386:43"/>Nulla Fides, pietas<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> viris, qui caſtra ſequuntur.</q> Or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with ſome reaſon, either going before, or immediately following after: as, <hi>Mortalis cùm ſis, inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citras immortales ne geras;</hi> Let not thy hatred be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, when thou thy ſelfe art otherwiſe. Sixtly and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it conſiſteth either of proper words; as, <hi>Vnicus Dei cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt, non eſſe malum:</hi> The onely worſhipping of God, is not to be a ſinner; or it is <hi>Tropicall:</hi> as here;
<q>
                     <l>Now ſtrike your ſailes, yee iolly Mariners,</l>
                     <l>For we be come vnto a quiet rode,<note place="margin">Spencer, Fa: Qu: lib <hi>1.</hi> Cant: <hi>12.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where we muſt land ſome of our Paſſengers,</l>
                     <l>And light this weary Veſſell of her lode.</l>
                  </q> As likewiſe in that of <hi>Maro's;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sed nos immenſum ſpacijs confecimus aequor,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Georgie: lib.</hi> 2. 1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Et iam tempus equûm fumantia ſoluere colla.</l>
                  </q> Which I will here applie vnto my ſelfe, as intending now to take a Fare-well of my <hi>Douely-Serpent;</hi> commending him to the conduct and protection of his mildeſt ſtarres: with this Apologie, to ſuch as ſhall embrace him in his trauailes; that I haue not faſhioned him, as <hi>Tullie</hi> did his Orator, in ſo hye a degree of perfection, that the reach of mans wiſedome is no way able to attaine vnto it. No, there is not any thing required heere, but paines and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie may eaſily effect. Yea, many (amongſt which, my ſelfe may happely be one) which ſeeme of ſuch a ſlender capacitie, that
<q>Boeotum in craſſo iurares aëre natos,</q> ceaſe not by daily imployments to become fit to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe great things.<note place="margin">Plin: lib: <hi>6.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Video</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plinie</hi> the ſecond) <hi>multos
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19386:44"/> paruo ingenio, literis nullis, vt bene agerent agendo conſecutos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> perſwaded the <hi>Athenians</hi> one day to buſie their Aſſes as well as their horſes in the tillage of their grounde. Wherevpon they anſwered him; that ſuch crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were neuer made for any ſuch purpoſe. That is all one, replyed he; it lyeth but in your will: For the moſt ignorant, and moſt vncapable men, that are employed by you in the commandements of your warres, let not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come moſt worthy, by being imployde by you. It is in Action, as it is in Speech, <hi>Vſus &amp; eſt, &amp; habetur optimus vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Magiſter:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Penelopen ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam perſtes, modo tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vinces: Capta vides ſerò Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, capta ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> Practiſe both is, and muſt bee ſtill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the beſt and trueſt Schoole-maiſter of both.</p>
               <p>Wherefore let no man alter his intended courſe, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie falſe ſurmiſed difficultie or tediouſneſſe in the way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inuia virtuti nulla eſt via.</hi> And it is an excellent <hi>Motto,</hi> and which becommeth well the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuements of a generous <hi>Spirit,</hi> 
                  <q>Non iuuat ex facili lecta corona iugo.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19386:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
